<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of independency, with the rise, growth, and practices of that powerfull and restlesse faction.</title>
            <author>Walker, Clement, 1595-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96821</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W329A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E445_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2013</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861823</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861823</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113968</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96821)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113968)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 70:E445[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of independency, with the rise, growth, and practices of that powerfull and restlesse faction.</title>
                  <author>Walker, Clement, 1595-1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous; attributed to Clement Walker.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 appeared in 1649 under the title "Anarchia Anglicana"; part 3 in 1651 under the title "The high court of justice".</note>
                  <note>Includes errata.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 26".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Roundheads --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Moral and ethical aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113968:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113968:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF INDEPENDENCY, WITH The Riſe, Growth, and Practices of that powerfull and reſtleſſe FACTION.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>D<hi rend="sup">us</hi> AMBROSIUS.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Nec nobis ignominioſum eſt pati quod paſſus eſt Chriſtus, nec vobis glorioſum eſt facere quod fecit Judas.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>TACIT:</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Scelera, ſceleribus, tuenda.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>VIRGILIUS.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>—ſua cuique Deus fit dira libido.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. JOHN C. 2. V. 16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Quicquid eſt in mundo eſt concupiſcentia oculorum, concupiſcentia carnis, aut ſuperbia vitae.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113968:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113968:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle or ungentle, <hi>I write to all,</hi> knowing that all have now got almoſt an equall ſhare and intereſt in this Gallymaufry or Hotchpot which our Grandee Pſeudo-politicians with their negative and demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing Councells have made, both of Church and Common-wealth: and therefore I write in <hi>a mixed ſtile,</hi> in which (I dare ſay) there are ſome things fit to hold the <hi>judgments of the Graveſt;</hi> ſome things fit to <hi>catch the fancies of the lighteſt,</hi> and ſome things of <hi>a middle nature,</hi> applying my ſelf to all capacities (as far as truth will permit) becauſe I fore-ſee the <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> of <hi>this Tragedy</hi> is more likely to be conſummated by <hi>mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of hands,</hi> then <hi>wiſdome of heads.</hi> I have been a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious obſerver, and a diligent inquirer, after, not only the <hi>actions,</hi> but the <hi>Councels of theſe times;</hi> and I here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the reſult of my endevours to thee: <hi>In a time of miſ-apprehenſions</hi> it is good to avoid <hi>miſtakings,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I adviſe thee not to apply what I ſay <hi>to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Army in generall,</hi> if any phraſe that hath drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from my pen in haſte (for this is a work of haſte) ſeem to look aſquint upon them: no, it is <hi>the Grandees,</hi> the <hi>Junto-men,</hi> the <hi>Hocas-pocaſſes,</hi> the <hi>State-Mountebanks,</hi> with their <hi>Zanyes</hi> and <hi>Jack-puddings, Committee-men,
<pb facs="tcp:113968:3"/> Sequestrators, Treaſurers,</hi> and <hi>Agitators,</hi> under them, that are here hiſtorified: were the <hi>Parliament</hi> (the major part whereof is in bondage to the minor part and their Janiſaries) and the <hi>Army</hi> freed from theſe uſurping and engaged <hi>Grandees,</hi> who betrayed the honour, and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament and Army to their own luſts; both would ſtand right, and be ſerviceable to the ſetling of a <hi>firme, laſting peace under the King:</hi> upon our <hi>firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, Religion, Laws, and Liberties;</hi> which are now ſo far laid by, that whoſoever will not joyne with the <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees</hi> in ſubvetting them, is tearmed a <hi>Malignant,</hi> as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore he that would <hi>not adhere to the Parliament</hi> in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting them was accounted, ſo that the <hi>definition</hi> of a <hi>Malignant</hi> is turned the wrong ſide outward. The body of the Parliament and Army in the midſt of theſe diſtempers) is yet healthy, ſound, ſerviceable; my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour is therefore to play the part of a friendly Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, and preſerve the body by purging peccant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours; were the Army under Commanders and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of better principles, who had not defiled their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers with <hi>publick monies,</hi> their conſciences by <hi>complying</hi> with, and <hi>cheating all Intereſts (King, Parliament, People, City,</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi>) for their owne private ends, I ſhould think that they carried the Sword of the Lord, and of <hi>Gideon;</hi> but clean contrary to the Image preſented to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> in a dream, the head and upper parts of this aggregate body are part of clay, part of iron, the lower parts of better mettle: I cannot reform, I can but admoniſh; God muſt be both the <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metheus,</hi> and amend all; and though we receive never ſo many <hi>denialls,</hi> never ſo many <hi>repulſes</hi> from him, let us take heed how we vote (even in the private corners of our hearts) no <hi>Addreſſes,</hi> no <hi>Applications</hi> to him. Let
<pb facs="tcp:113968:3"/> us take heed of multiplying ſins againſt God, leſt he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our <hi>ſchiſmaticall Grandees to multiply Armies and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> upon us, to war againſt Heaven as well as againſt our Religion, Laws, Liberties &amp; Properties upon Earth, and keep us &amp; our Eſtates under the perpetual bondage of the Sword, which hath been ſeverall waies attempted in the Houſes theſe two laſt weeks, both for the <hi>raiſing and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of a new Army of</hi> 30000. <hi>or</hi> 40000. <hi>men in the ſeven Northern Aſſociate Counties, upon eſtabliſhed pay (beſides this Army in the South)</hi> and alſo for the <hi>raiſing of men in each County of England,</hi> and all to be engroſſed into the hands of his Excellency, and ſuch Commanders and Officers as he ſhall ſet over them; and this work may chance be carried on by the Grandees of <hi>Derby-houſe</hi> and the Army, if not prevented; for the Generall (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this power was denied him in the Houſe of Commons) hath ſent Warrants into moſt Counties to raiſe Horſe and Foot; yea, to that baſeneſſe of ſlavery hath our Generall and Army, with their under-Tyrants the Grandees brought us, that although themſelves did heretofore ſet the <hi>raſcallity</hi> of the Kingdome on worke, (eſpecially the <hi>ſchiſmaticall party</hi>) to clamour upon the Parliament with <hi>ſcandalous Petitions,</hi> and make peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory demands to the Houſes, deſtructive to the <hi>Religion, Laws, Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties of the Land,</hi> and the very <hi>foundation of Parliaments:</hi> to which, they extorted what Anſwers they pleaſed: and got a generall Vote, <hi>That it was the undoubted right of the Subject to petition, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to acquieſce in the wiſdome and juſtice of the two Houſes:</hi> Yet when upon 16. of <hi>May,</hi> 1648. the whole County of <hi>Surrey</hi> (in effect) came in ſo civill a poſture to deliver a Petition to the Houſes, that they were armed for the moſt part but with ſticks: in which Petition there
<pb facs="tcp:113968:4"/> is <hi>nothing contained which the Parliament is not bound to make good</hi> by their many <hi>Declarations and Remonſtrances</hi> to the people, or by the <hi>Oaths of Allegiance, Supremacy,</hi> or <hi>Nationall Covenant,</hi> or by <hi>the known Lawes of this Land.</hi> Yet were they, 1. Abuſed by the Souldiers of <hi>White-Hall</hi> as they paſſed by, where ſome of them were pulled in and beaten. 2. When thoſe Gentlemen of quality that carried the Petition came to <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> they found a Guard of Souldiers at the dore unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy oppoſing their entrance to make their addreſſe to the Houſe. 3. When they preſſed into the Hall and got up to the Commons dore, they were there reviled by the Guard. 4. The multitude which ſtood in the <hi>new Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace,</hi> (becauſe ſome of them did but whoop as others did, who were purpoſely ſet on work (as is conceived) to mix with them, and diſorder them) were ſuddenly ſurrounded with a ſtrong party of Horſe from the <hi>Mewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">It is reported by ſome, that Sir <hi>H. Mildmay,</hi> Col. <hi>Purefoy,</hi> and the <hi>Speaker</hi> (doubting the Houſe would give too good an Anſwer to their Petition) ſent for theſe Horſe &amp; Foot.</note> and ſome more Companies of Foot from <hi>White-Hall,</hi> who by the appointment of the Committee of Schiſmaticks at <hi>Derby-houſe</hi> were ready prepared for this deſigne, and catched them (as it were) in a Toyle, and with barbarous and ſchiſmaticall rage fell upon theſe naked, un-armed Petitioners, flew and wounded many without diſtinction, telling them, <hi>They were appointed to give an Anſwer to their Petition, and they ſhould have no other;</hi> (as indeed they had not) though the Lieutenant Colonel that did all the miſchief was called into the Houſe of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons, and had publick thanks given him at the Bar) took many of them Priſoners, and Plundred their Pockets, Cloaks, Hats, Swords, Horſes, and ſome of them (even Gentlemen of as good quality as their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall) were ſtripped of their Doublets. Thoſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of quality who were in the <hi>Lobby</hi> before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons dore civilly expecting an Anſwer, were abuſed,
<pb facs="tcp:113968:4"/> and violently driven out by the Guard to take their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune amongſt the rabble; what <hi>Tyrants</hi> ever in the world <hi>refuſed to hear the Petitions</hi> and grievances of their people before? The moſt Tyrannical government of the world is that of <hi>Ruſsia,</hi> and <hi>John Vaſilowich</hi> was the greateſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of that Nation, yet ſhall this Tyrant riſe up in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the latter day againſt theſe monſters. Behold what entertainment your Petitions ſhall have hereafter, if publick peace be the end of their deſires: yet many Petitions ready drawne are ſent up and downe in moſt Counties by Committee-men, and Sequeſtrators, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force men to give thanks for the foure Votes againſt the King: And many Petitions from Schiſmaticks, deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to Religion, Laws, Liberties and Property, have been obtruded upon the Houſes, and received encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and thanks becauſe they tend to <hi>ſubvert the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall government</hi> of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and caſt all into the <hi>Chaos of confuſion,</hi> whereby the <hi>Grandees may have occaſion to keep up this Army,</hi> and perpetuate their Tiranny and our Burdens. And from theſe Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults of their own raiſing, the Grandees pretend a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to keep this Army about this Town, to watch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages againſt it: <hi>Cromwell</hi> having often ſaid, <hi>This Town muſt be brought to more abſolute obedience, or laid in the duſt;</hi> in order to which the <hi>Souldiers are now diſ-ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Country,</hi> and <hi>then the City</hi> is next, who being once diſ-armed, muſt proſtitute their <hi>mony-bags</hi> to theſe fellows, or be <hi>plundred.</hi> Reader, having ſpoken my ſence to thee, I leave thee to thy own ſence; ſubmitting my ſelf to as much charity as God hath endowed thee withall. <hi>God that made all, preſerve and amend all,</hi> This ſhall be the daily prayer of him that had rather die for his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, then ſhare with theſe <hi>Godly Thieves</hi> in eating out the bowels of his Country, and enriching himſelf with pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſpoiles.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:113968:5"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped, correct thus:</head>
            <p>PAg. 1. lin. 21. read <hi>their differenees.</hi> p. 9. l. 23. r. <hi>hath been.</hi> p. 15. l. 1. r. <hi>publike Proclamation.</hi> ibid. l. 37. r. <hi>had to do to.</hi> p. 16. l. 13. r. <hi>ſelf-defence.</hi> p. 17. marg. l. 6. r. <hi>by whom.</hi> p. 18. l. 20. r. <hi>Court of Requeſt.</hi> p. 29. l. 8. r. <hi>whereof you.</hi> p. 49. l. 21. r. <hi>rock is.</hi> p. 51. l. 21. r. <hi>friend into.</hi> ib. l. 25. r. <hi>Presbyterian Commoners.</hi> p. 53. l. 22. <hi>Peaces place.</hi> p. 56. l. 32. r. <hi>Trained Band.</hi> p. 61. l. 22. r. <hi>promiſing to.</hi> ib. l. 23. r. <hi>deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the.</hi> p. 66. l. 1. r. <hi>inſtructions to ſtay.</hi> ib. l. 24. r. <hi>Counties.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113968:5"/>
            <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>INDEPENDENCY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou have in <hi>The myſtery of the two Juntoes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Preamble.</note> PRES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BYTERIAN and INDEPENDENT, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to your view theſe two Factions, (as it were in a Cock-pit pecking at one another) which ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing originally from the two Houſes and Synod have ſo much diſturbed and diſlocated in every joynt both Church and Common-wealth. I muſt now ſet before you <hi>Independency</hi> Triumphant, rouzing it ſelf upon its Legs, clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping its Wings, and Crowing in the midſt of the Pit, with its ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my under its feet: though not yet well reſolved what uſe it can or may make of its victory.</p>
            <p>But before I go any farther,<note n="1" place="margin">1. What Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency is.</note> it is fit I tell you what <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency</hi> is:</p>
            <p>It is <hi>Genus generaliſſimum</hi> of all Errours, Hereſies, Blaſphemies and Schiſmes. A generall name and Title under which they are all united, as <hi>Sampſon's</hi> Foxes were by the <hi>Tailes;</hi> and though they have ſeverall opinions and fancies (which make their <hi>verti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginous heads</hi> turne different waies) yet profit and preferment (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>tailes</hi>) their laſt and ultimate end by which they are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned (like a Ship by his Rudder) and wherein they mutually correſpond. The reſt of your differences being but circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall are eaſily playſter'd over with the <hi>untempered morter</hi> of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie by their <hi>Rabbies</hi> of the Aſſembly, and their <hi>Grandees</hi> of the two Houſes and Army, in whom they have an <hi>implicite faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Mahomet's</hi> Alchoran was a Gallemaufry of Jew and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; ſo are they a Compoſition of <hi>Jew, Chriſtian,</hi> and <hi>Turk.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Independency is compounded of Iudaiſme.</note> With the Jew they arrogate to be the peculiar people of God,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113968:6"/> the Godly, the Saints, who onely have right unto the creatures, and ſhould poſſeſſe the good things of this world, all others being Uſurpers: A Tenent ſo deſtructive to all humane ſociety and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill government, that by virtue thereof they may and doe by fraud, or force, Tax, eate up with Free-quarter, couſen, and Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the whole Kingdome, and account it but robbing the Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians: To this purpoſe they overthrow all the Judicatories, Laws, and Liberties of the Land, and ſet up Arbitrary Committees, and <hi>weather-cock</hi> Ordinances in their room, <hi>made</hi> and <hi>unmade</hi> by their own over-powering Faction in Parliament at pleaſure, with the help and terrour of their Janiſaries, attending at their dores.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Chriſtianiſme.</note>With the Chriſtians ſome of them (but not all) acknowledge the Scripture, but ſo far onely as they will ſerve their turns, to <hi>Phariſee</hi> themſelves, and <hi>Publican</hi> all the world beſides; men filled with ſpirituall pride, meer Enthuſiaſtiques, of a ſpeculative and high-flying Religion, too high for Earth, and too low for Heaven: whereas a true and fruitfull Religion like <hi>Jacob's</hi> lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>Stat pede in terris, caput inter nubila condit;</hi> muſt have one end upon earth as well as the other in Heaven. He that acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the duties of the firſt Table to God, and neglecteth the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſecond Table to man, is an Hypocrite both againſt God and man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Turciſme.</note>With the Turke they ſubject all things, even <hi>Religion, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> (ſo much cried up by them heretofore) to the power of the ſword, ever ſince by undermining practiſes and lies they have jugled the <hi>States ſword</hi> into the <hi>Independent ſcabbard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="2" place="margin">2. The E. of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Will: Waller</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to let in the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.</note>The Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> Generall of all the Parliaments Forces (a man though popular and honeſt, yet ſtubbornly ſtout, fitter for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction then Counſell, and apter to get a Victory then improve it) muſt be laid by, and his Forces reduced. The like for Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> and his Forces, that Commanders of <hi>Independent</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and intereſts with Souldiers ſutable to them, might by degrees be brought into their room to reap the harveſt of thoſe crops which they had ſowen.</p>
            <p>This was the ground-work of the <hi>Independent</hi> deſigne, to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolize the power of the Sword into their own hands.</p>
            <p>This could not be better effected then by daſhing the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> one againſt another: for which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113968:6"/> purpoſe that hot-headed Schiſmatique Sir <hi>A. Haſlerigge</hi> was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed with Sir <hi>W. Waller</hi> and ſome others (whoſe Aſhes I will ſpare) with the E. of <hi>Eſſex</hi> to break them one upon another. This was at laſt effected by taking advantage of their ſeverall misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; the one at <hi>Listithyell</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> the other at the <hi>Deviſes</hi> in <hi>Wiltſh.</hi> where <hi>Haſterigge</hi> (a man too ignorant to command, and too inſolent to obey) not ſtaying for the Foot who lay round about the <hi>Deviſes</hi> in a ſtorming poſture, charged up a ſteep hill with his Horſe only againſt the Lord <hi>Wilmot's</hi> Party, one Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion ſo far before another, that the ſecond Diviſion could not relieve the firſt, thereby freeing Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton</hi> from an aſſured overthrow, and beſtowing an unexpected Victory on the L. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mot:</hi> he received a wound in his flight, the ſmart whereof is ſtill ſo powerfully imprinted in his memory, that he abhors fighting e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince; witneſſe his praying and crying out of Gun-ſhot at the Battle of <hi>Cheriton,</hi> when he ſhould have fought; and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint openly made in the Houſe of Commons of the Earle of <hi>Stanford</hi> for Baſtonadoing him. Which raſhneſſe of his (if it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve not a worſe name) was ſo far from being diſcountenanced, that he received not long after a gift of 6500l. from the Houſe, and is lately made Governour of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> and 3000l. given him to repaire the Works there. I ſhall not need the ſpirit of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to foreſee that the tenth part of the ſaid 3000l. will not be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon thoſe Works. Thus was he favoured by his party in the Houſe who were thought to look upon this action as an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable ſervice.</p>
            <p>In farther progreſſe of this deſigne <hi>Mancheſter</hi> (a Lord,<note n="3" place="margin">3. The E. of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</note> and therefore not to be confided in) was undermined and accuſed by his Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> of high Crimes, whom he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain recriminated with a Charge of as high a nature; and when all men were high in expectation of the event, it grew to be a drawn battle between them; whereby all men concluded them both guilty: <hi>Manchester</hi> was diſcarded.</p>
            <p>Out of the aſhes of theſe three aroſe that Phoenix (forſooth) a new modell'd Army under the Command of Sir <hi>Thomas Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax,</hi> a Gentleman of an irrationall and brutiſh valour, fitter to follow another mans counſell then his owne, and obnoxious to <hi>Cromwell</hi> and the <hi>Independent faction</hi> (upon whoſe bottome he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113968:7"/> ſtands) for his preferment, it being no diſhonour to him to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the property to a powerfull Faction.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="4" place="margin">4. The Victories of the new Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell how at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieved.</note>It pleaſed God to beſtow many Victories upon this Army over the Kings Forces; then ſtrong in bulk, but weakned by Factions, want of Pay and other diſtractions (whereby many of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders not confiding in one another, began to provide for their future ſafety and ſubſiſtence) but above all, they had generally loſt the peoples affections. To theſe their Victories, the conſtant pay, and ſupplies, and all other helps and encouragements from a concurring State, which their working and reſtleſſe Faction care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully accommodated them withall (far beyond what any other Army had formerly) did much conduce, in ſo much as they clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the field, and took in all the enemies Garriſons with ſo much facility, that to many men they ſeemed rather <hi>Cauponantes bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum quàm belligerantes,</hi> to Conquer with ſilver then with ſteel.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="5" place="margin">5. Artifices to make <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his new Modell po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular.</note>Thus this Faction having got a Generall fit for their turne, and a Lieutenant Generall wholly theirs in Judgment and intereſt, were diligent to make him famous and popular, by caſting upon him the honour of other mens Atchievements and valour. The News-books taught to ſpeak no language but <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his Party; and were mute in ſuch actions as he and they could claim no ſhare in: for which purpoſe the Preſſes were narrowly wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. When any great exploit was half atchieved, and the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties overcome, <hi>Cromwell</hi> was ſent to finiſh it, and take the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to himſelf, all other men muſt be eclipſed that <hi>Cromwell</hi> (the <hi>Knight of the Sun</hi> and <hi>Don Quixote</hi> of the <hi>Independents</hi>) and his Party may ſhine the brighter.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="6" place="margin">6. The new Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell new-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delled by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to put the Sword into the hands of Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks.</note>And that <hi>Cromwell's</hi> Army might be ſutable to himſelf, and their Deſignes carried on without interruption or obſervation of ſuch as are not of their Principles, all the Sectaries of <hi>England</hi> are invited to be Reſerves to this Army; and all pretences of ſcandals and crimes laid hold of at their owne Councels of War to caſheer and disband the <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> party, that <hi>Independents</hi> might be let into their rooms, though ſuch as (for the moſt part) never drew Sword before: ſo that this Army (which boaſteth it ſelf for the Deliverer, nay the Conquerour of two Kingdoms) is no more the ſame that fought at <hi>Nazeby,</hi> then Sir <hi>Francis Drake's</hi> Ship that brought him home can be called the ſame Ship that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113968:7"/> him forth about the earth, having been ſo often repaired, and thereby ſuffered ſo many ſubſtractions and additions, that hardly any part of the old Veſſell remained. It was therefore <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minally</hi> and <hi>formally,</hi> not <hi>really</hi> and <hi>materially</hi> the ſame.</p>
            <p>The ſaid <hi>Myſtery of the two Junto's</hi> farther tells you, that the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Junto</hi> bottomed all their hopes and intereſts upon kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping up this Army; whereby to give the Law to King, Kingdom, Parliament, and City, and to eſtabliſh that <hi>Chimaera</hi> called <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conſcience.</hi> That this was <hi>Cromwell's</hi> ambition formerly, the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter's</hi> aforeſaid Charge againſt <hi>Cromwell</hi> (though let fall without proſecution, leſt ſo great a myſtery ſhould be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered) makes it probable, and his later practiſes (upon which I now fall) makes it infallible.</p>
            <p>The Houſes long ſince (for eaſe of the people) in a full and free Parliament ordained the disbanding of this Army,<note n="7" place="margin">7. The Army Voted to be Disbanded through <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well's</hi> craft.</note> onely 5000 Horſe 1000 Dragoons, and ſome few Fire-locks to be continued in pay for ſafety of this Kingdome, and ſome of them to be ſent for <hi>Ireland:</hi> for which purpoſe they borrowed 200000l. of the City, (being the ſame ſumme which disbanded the <hi>Scots</hi>) and for the reſt of their Arrears they were to have Debenters and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, without all exceptions: ſuch tearms of advantage as no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther disbanded Souldiers have had the like; neither are theſe like to attain to again; ſo that they have brought the Souldiers into a <hi>loſſe,</hi> as well as into a <hi>labyrinth:</hi> their continuing in Armes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, nay againſt <hi>lawfull authority,</hi> being a manifeſt act of <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Rebellion;</hi> and ſo it is looked upon by the whole Kingdome; nor can the Parliaments ſubſequent Ordinances, (which all men know to be extorted by force, as hereafter ſhall appear) help them.</p>
            <p>To the paſſing of this Ordinance <hi>Cromwell's</hi> Proteſtations in the Houſe with his hand upon his breſt, <hi>In the preſence of Almighty God before whom he ſtood, that he knew the Army would diſband and lay downe their Armes at their dore, whenſoever they ſhould command them,</hi> conduced much: This was malitiouſly done of <hi>Cromwell</hi> to ſet the Army at a greater diſtance with the <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian</hi> Party, and bring them and the <hi>Independents</hi> Party neerer together; he knew the Army abominated nothing more then Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding and returning to their old Trades: and wduld hate the Authors thereof.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113968:8"/>
            <p>
               <note n="8" place="margin">8. Agitators rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Cromwel.</hi>
               </note> 
               <note n="9" place="margin">9. The beginning of the project to purge the Houſes.</note> 
               <note n="10" place="margin">10. The Army put into mutiny a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>Cromwell</hi> monopolizeth the Army.</note>And at the ſame time when he made theſe <hi>proteſts</hi> in the Houſe, he had his <hi>Agitators (Spirits</hi> of his and his Son <hi>Ireton's conjuring up</hi> in the Army, though ſince <hi>conjured downe</hi> by them without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall) to animate them againſt the major part of the Houſe (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of <hi>Royalliſts,</hi> a Malignant party, and enemies to the Army) to ingage them againſt Disbanding and going for <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and to make a Trayterous Comment upon the ſaid Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to demand an <hi>Act of indemnity,</hi> and relie upon the advice of Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> for the validity of it, and to inſiſt upon many other high demands, ſome private, as Souldiers; ſome publick, as States-men.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="11" place="margin">11. <hi>Cromwell's</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily in the Army.</note>
               <hi>Cromwell</hi> having thus by mutinying the Army againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, made them his owne, and <hi>monopolized</hi> them, as he did formerly his <hi>Brew-houſe at Ely</hi> (which he might eaſily do, having before-hand filled moſt of the chief Offices in the Army with his owne kindred, allyes, and friends: of whoſe numerous family, Lieut. Col. <hi>Lilburne</hi> gives you a liſt in one of his Books) he now flies to the Army, doubting (his practiſes diſcovered) he might be impriſoned:<note n="12" place="margin">12. <hi>Cromwell</hi> and <hi>Ireton</hi> uſurp Offices in the Army.</note> where he and <hi>Ireton</hi> aſſuming Offices to themſelves, acted without Commiſſion; having not only been ouſted by the <hi>ſelf-denying Ordinance</hi> (if it be of any power againſt the godly) but alſo their ſeverall Commiſſions being then expired: and Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> having no authority to make generall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, as appears by his Commiſſion, (if he make any account of it) and therefore <hi>Sprigg,</hi> alias <hi>Nathaniel Fines,</hi> in his Legend or Romance of this Army, called <hi>Anglia rediviva,</hi> ſets down two Letters ſent from Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> to the Speaker <hi>William Lenthall,</hi> one to deſire <hi>Cromwell's</hi> continuance in the Army: an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of thanks for ſo long forbearing him from the Houſe: ſee <hi>Ang. Red. p.</hi> 10, 11, 29. which needed not, had he been an Officer of the Army.</p>
            <p>And now both of them bare-faced, and openly joyne with the Army at <hi>Newmarket,</hi> in trayterous Engagements, Declarations, Remonſtrances, and Manifeſto's; and Petitions penn'd by <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> himſelf, were ſent to ſome Counties to be ſubſcribed againſt ſuppoſed Obſtructers of Juſtice, and Invaders of the Peoples Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties in Parliament, and the Army at <hi>Newmarket</hi> and <hi>Triplo</hi> heath prompted to cry Juſtice, Juſtice, againſt them; and high
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113968:8"/> and treaſonable demands, deſtructive to the fundamentall Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament were publickly inſiſted upon; many of which for quietneſſe ſake, and out of compaſſion to bleeding <hi>Ireland</hi> were granted: yet theſe reſtleſſe ſpirits (hurried on to farther deſignes) made one impudent demand beget another; and when by Letters and otherwiſe they had promiſed, that if their then preſent demands were granted, they would there ſtop and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce, yet when they ſeemed to have done, they had not done, but deluded and evaded all hopes of peace by miſ-apprehenſions and miſ-conſtructions of the Parliaments conceſſions; making the miſ-interpretation of one grant, the generation of another demand, ſo that almoſt ever ſince the Parliament hath nothing elſe to do but encounter this <hi>Hydra,</hi> and <hi>roll this ſtone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus debauched the Army,<note n="13" place="margin">13. Securing <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring the King from <hi>Holdenby.</hi>
               </note> he plotted in his own Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the ſecuring the Garriſons, Magazine, and Traine of Artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and ſurprizing the Kings Perſon at <hi>Holdenby:</hi> which by his inſtrument Coronet <hi>Joyce,</hi> with a commanded Party of Horſe he effected: though afterwards (having recourſe to his u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall <hi>familiarity with Almighty God</hi>) he uſed his name to proteſt his ignorance and innocence in that buſineſſe both to the King and Parliament; adding an execration upon his Wife and Children to his Proteſtation; yet <hi>Joyce</hi> is ſo free from puniſhment, that he is ſince preferred, and his Arrears paid by their meanes. And though both Houſes required the Army to ſend his Royall Perſon to <hi>Richmond,</hi> to be there left in the hands of the Parliaments Commiſſioners, whereby both Kingdoms might freely make Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to Him; (for they had formerly excluded and abuſed the Scots Commiſſioners, contrary to the Law of Nations, and Votes of both Houſes; and yet then granted free acceſſe to the moſt deſperate perſons of the Kings Party) yet they could obtaine no better anſwer from theſe <hi>rebellious Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Manifeſto</hi> of the Army, 27. <hi>June</hi> 1647.</note> then <hi>That they deſired no place might be propoſed for His Majeſties reſidence neerer London, then where they would allow the Quarters of the Army to be.</hi> This was according to their old threats of marching up to <hi>London,</hi> fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently uſed, when any thing went contrary to their deſires. They knew what dangerous and troubleſome gueſts we ſhould find them here.</p>
            <p>How much is this Army degenerated ſince <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113968:9"/> demure white-livered Son-in-law <hi>Ireton</hi> poyſoned their manners with new Principles? <hi>Anglia Rediviva, p.</hi> 247. tells us that about <hi>Woodſtock</hi> private overtures were made by ſome from Court for receiving His Majeſty, who was minded to caſt himſelf upon the Army: but ſuch was their faithfulneſſe in that poynt, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it derogatory to the honour and power of Parliament, (for His Majeſty to wave that higheſt Court, and addreſſe Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to any others) and therefore inconſiſtent with their truſt and duty, being Servants of the State, they certified the Parliament thereof, and underſtanding it to be againſt their ſenſe alſo, they abſolutely refuſed to be tampered with. Oh, how faithfull then! how perfidious and <hi>Cromwellized</hi> are they now! let their fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent tampering with the King and His Party, to the amazement of the Kingdome, and the abuſing of the King teſtifie. Read <hi>Put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Projects</hi> written by a conſiderable Officer of the Army, and a friend to <hi>Cromwell,</hi> though not to his falſe practiſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="14" place="margin">14. Their project to keep the Parliament in wardſhip.</note> 
               <note n="15" place="margin">15. Purging the Houſes again.</note> 
               <note n="16" place="margin">16. Accuſing the 11 Members.</note>Having thus gotten the <hi>King</hi> (the <hi>firſt</hi> and moſt viſible legall authority of <hi>England</hi>) into their poſſeſſion; their next deſigne is to get the <hi>Parliament</hi> (the <hi>ſecond</hi> legall authority of <hi>England</hi>) into their power.</p>
            <p>This could not be effected but by purging the two Houſes of <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Members (eſpecially the moſt active, and ſuch as had laboured their Disbanding) that an <hi>Independent</hi> Parliament and Army might govern the Kingdome: In order to which deſigne they ſent to the Houſe of Commons in the name of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> and the <hi>Army,</hi> a generall and confuſed Charge of High Treaſons and other miſ-demeanors againſt <hi>eleven</hi> Members, for things done (for the moſt part in the Houſe) and many of the principall, ſuch as the Houſe had long before examined and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted them of, and ſuch as the whole Kingdome knows <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> and <hi>Ireton</hi> to be apparently guilty of: as, <hi>Trucking with the King, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One chief Article inſiſted upon in the Charge was, <hi>That by their power in the Houſe they cauſed the Ordinance for Diſbanding this Army to paſſe.</hi> Here you ſee where the ſhooe wrings them. This Charge was not ſubſcribed by any Informer that ingaged to make it good, or elſe to ſuffer puniſhment, and make the Houſe and the Parties accuſed reparations: as by the <hi>Stat.</hi> 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113968:9"/> 27 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 18. 38 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9. 17 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 6. 15 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 4. but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by 31 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 1. concerning <hi>Jack Cade</hi> (which comes neareſt this caſe) ought to be: And they profeſſed in the 2, 3, 4. Article of their Charge, <hi>That they were diſobliged and diſcouraged from any farther engagement in the Parliaments ſervice or Irelands preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and demanded the Houſe ſhould forthwith ſuspend the impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Members from any longer ſitting and acting.</hi> Whereupon the Houſe after full debate in a full and free Parliament, Reſolved <hi>June</hi> 25. 1647. That by the Lawes of the Land no Judgement could be given for their ſuſpenſion upon that generall Charge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore particulars produced and proofes made.<note n="17" place="margin">17. Threates to march up to <hi>London.</hi>
               </note> 
               <note n="18" place="margin">18. <hi>London</hi> ſolicited to ſit Newters.</note> Yet the Army (which had now learned onely to acquieſce in their owne pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and juſtice) inſolently threatned to march up to <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> againſt the Parliament, in caſe the ſaid 11. Members were not ſuſpended: and courted the City of <hi>London</hi> to ſit newters, and let them work their will with the Parliament.</p>
            <p>The 11. Impeached Members therefore modeſtly withdrew to free the Houſe from ſuch danger as they might incur by protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, as in Juſtice and Honour they were bound to doe. After this, the Army ſent in their particular Charge: and Libellouſly publiſhed it in Print by their own Authority. To which the 11 Members ſent in, and publiſhed their Anſwer: Upon which there had been no Proſecution, becauſe they pretend firſt to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the Kingdome, but if they ſtay till theſe fellowes have either authority, will, or skill to ſettle the Kingdome, they ſhall not need to make ready for their Tryall till Doomes day. Here you have a whole Army for Accuſers, and the chief Officers of the Army (being Members of the Houſe) not onely accuſers, but parties, witneſſes, and Judges, and carrying the rules of Court, and Lawes by which they judge, in their Scaberds. And the Charge or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment, ſuch (as all men know) <hi>mutatis mutandis</hi> are more ſutable to <hi>Cromwells</hi> and <hi>Iretons</hi> Actions, then the Accuſed par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. If the proceedings in the Kings name againſt the five Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers mentioned in <hi>The exact Collection, pag.</hi> 38. were Voted <hi>a Traiterous deſigne againſt King and Parliament;</hi> and the arreſting any of them upon the Kings Warrant, <hi>an Act of publick enmity againſt the Common-wealth:</hi> How much more <hi>Treaſonable</hi> were theſe proceedings; and the Armies March towards <hi>London</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113968:10"/> them; and their arreſting <hi>Anthony Nicholls,</hi> having the Speakers Paſſe, and leave of the Houſe; Colonell <hi>Burch,</hi> being upon ſervice of the Parliament going for <hi>Ireland;</hi> and Sir <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Luke,</hi> reſting quiet in his owne Houſe?</p>
            <p>
               <note n="19" place="margin">19. The firſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of quarrell againſt the City.</note> 
               <note n="20" place="margin">20. Courting and cheating the Country and all other inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts to lull t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em aſleep, till the Grandees had wrought their will upon City &amp; Houſes.</note> 
               <note n="21" place="margin">21 Petitions to the Army, and for the Army.</note>Whilſt theſe things were acting, <hi>Cromwell</hi> finding he could not have his will upon the Parliament, but that he muſt make the City of <hi>London</hi> (who had denyed the newtrality) his Enemies, caſt about how to cheat the Country people of their affections; (for to have both City and Country his Enemies in the poſture his Army was then in, was dangerous) he therefore by many Printed books and papers, ſpread all <hi>England</hi> over by his <hi>Agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators,</hi> and by ſome journey-men Prieſts, (who's <hi>Pulpits</hi> are the beſt <hi>Juglers Boxes</hi> to deceive the ſimple) <hi>Abſolon</hi>-like, wooeth them to make loud complaints of the preſſures and grievances of the People: to neglect the King and the Parliament, and make Addreſſes to the Army as their only <hi>Saviours,</hi> the Arbitrators of Peace, reſtorers of our Laws, Liberties and Properties, ſetlers of Religion, preſervers of all juſt intereſts: pretending to ſettle the King in his juſt Rights and Prerogatives; to uphold the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of Parliament, eſtabliſh Religion, to reforme, and bring to accompt all Committees, Sequeſtrators, and all others that had defiled their fingers with publique money, or goods; To free the people from that all-devouring Exciſe and other Taxes; To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe undue elections of Members; To relieve <hi>Ireland:</hi> Things impoſſible to be performed by an Army, and now totally for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, ſo that they have only accepted of their own private de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands as Souldiers; That the Parliament ſhould own them for their Army; Eſtabliſh pay for them; put the whole Militia of this Kingdome and <hi>Ireland,</hi> both by Sea and Land into their Hands; and Vote againſt all oppoſite forces. But they are now become the only protectors of all corrupt Committee-men, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrators, Accomptants to the State, and all other facinorous perſons, who comply with them to keep up this Army, for their own ſecurity againſt publick Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Having thus courted and cheated all the publike and juſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of the Kingdome, they deceived the people ſo far as to make them <hi>Iſſachar</hi>-like patiently to bear the <hi>burden</hi> of <hi>free quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and to make addreſſes to the Army for themſelves, by Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113968:10"/> to which they gave plauſible anſwers, That <hi>this,</hi> and <hi>This</hi> was <hi>the ſenſe of the Army:</hi> as if the ſenſe of the Army had been the ſupream Law of the Land, and to make addreſſes to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Army not to be <hi>diſbanded</hi> (for which purpoſe their <hi>Agitators</hi> carried Petitions ready penn'd to be ſubſcribed in moſt Counties.)</p>
            <p>The people being thus lulled aſleep,<note n="22" place="margin">22 A quarrell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the City invented.</note> they now caſt about how to make benefit of a joynt quarrell both againſt the Parliament and City, (ſince they could not ſeparate them) or at leaſt againſt the Presbyterian party in both; They had withdrawn their <hi>quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> (in a ſeeming obedience to Parliaments commands) 30 miles from <hi>London,</hi> (of which they often brag in their Papers) and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed the ſuſpenſion of the 11 <hi>Members,</hi> had ſtrook ſuch an aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe into the Houſes, that moſt of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Members would either abſent themſelves (as too many indeed did) or turn renegadoes from their own principles to them: but found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves notwithſtanding oppoſed, and their deſires retarded (beyond their expectation) by the remainder of that Party. They muſt therefore finde out a quarrell to march againſt the City, and give the Houſes another <hi>Purge</hi> ſtronger then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
            <p>The Army being principled,<note n="23" place="margin">23 The Army de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the City Militia to be changed into other hands.</note> and put into a poſture ſutable to <hi>Cromwells</hi> deſire, and the Country charmed into a dull ſleep, now was his time to pick a quarrell with the City, that what he could not obtain by fair means, he might effect by foule; To make them deſert and divide from the Parliament; And leave it to be modelled according to the diſcretion of the Souldiery. He could not think it agreeable to policy, that this City which had ſlaine his Compeere and fellow Prince <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> (the Idoll of the Commons in <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. time) and routed his followers (four times as many in number as his Army) ſhould be truſted with their own Militia: The City being now far greater, more populous and powerfull then in his dayes. In a full and free Parliament upon mature debate, both Houſes by Ordinance dated 4 <hi>May</hi> 1647. had eſtabliſhed the <hi>Militia of the City</hi> of <hi>London</hi> for a <hi>year,</hi> in the hands of ſuch Citizens as by their Authority &amp; approbation were nominated by the Lord Major, Aldermen, and Common-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell; and though the Army had recruited it ſelf without Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113968:11"/> and had got themſelves inveſted with the whole power of all the Land forces of the Kingdome in pay of the Parliament; ſo that there was nothing left that could be <hi>formidable</hi> to them but <hi>their own crimes;</hi> and that it was expected they ſhould goe roundly to work upon thoſe publick remedies they had ſo often held forth to the people in their popular printed Papers: yet the Army (contrary to what they promiſed to the City in their <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 10. <hi>June,</hi> and their <hi>Declaration,</hi> or Repreſentation 14. <hi>June</hi> 1647. That they would not goe beyond their deſires at that time expreſſed, and for other particulars would acquieſce in the juſtice and wiſdome of the Parliament (behold their modeſty!) by a <hi>Letter</hi> and <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> from Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,<note place="margin">See the Letter and Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance from Sir <hi>Tho. Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax</hi> and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, <hi>pag</hi> 8, 9.</note> with unreſiſtible boldneſſe demand the <hi>Militia</hi> of the City of <hi>London</hi> to be returned into other hands, without acquainting the City or their Commiſſioners (then reſident in the Army to keep a good correſpondency with them) therewith. Upon which letter alone the Houſe of Commons (being very thin, &amp; many Members driven away by menaces) upon <hi>July</hi> 22. Voted the repealing the ſaid Vote of 4 <hi>May,</hi> and a new Ordinance for reviving the <hi>old Militia,</hi> preſently paſſed and tranſmitted to the Lords the ſame day about ſeven of the clock at night, and there preſently paſſed without debate; though moved by ſome to be put off untill the City (whoſe ſafety and priviledges it highly concerned) were heard what they could ſay to it.</p>
            <p>Obſerve that neither by the ſaid paper from the Army; nor by any man in the two Houſes, any thing was objected againſt any of the <hi>new Militia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, formerly the Parliament never made choice of, enlarged or changed the City <hi>Militia,</hi> but they were ſtill pleaſed firſt to communicate the ſame to the Common Councell. A re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect juſtly ſhewed to that City which had been ſuch good friends to them. But of late, ſince the Parliament have ſhifted their old Principles and Intereſts, they have learned to lay by their old friends. The pretence for this haſty paſſing the Ordinance, was to prevent the Armies ſo much threatned March to <hi>London,</hi> if the Houſes refuſed to paſſe it; and the Cities oppoſition, if not paſſed before their notice of it. But the reall deſigne was to ſtrike a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content and jealouſie into the City, thereby to force them to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113968:11"/> ſome act of ſelf-defence, which might give a colour to the Army to march up againſt them, and their friends in the Houſes.</p>
            <p>The unexpected news of this changing their <hi>Militia,</hi>
               <note n="24" place="margin">24. The City trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at the change of their <hi>Militia.</hi>
               </note> cauſed the City (<hi>June</hi> 24. being Saturday) to meet in Common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, where, (for ſome reaſons already expreſſed) and becauſe the repealing this Ordinance upon no other grounds then the Armies imperious deſires, might juſtly be ſuſpected, to ſhake all other Ordinances, for ſecurity of mony, ſale of Biſhops lands,<note place="margin">I appeal to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Harvy</hi> whether this did not fright him.</note> by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them repealable at the Armies pleaſure; they reſolved to petition the Houſes upon munday morning following, being 26. <hi>July,</hi> which they did by the Sheriffs, and ſome Common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell men:<note n="25" place="margin">25. The City peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for their <hi>Militia</hi> again.</note> 
               <note n="26" place="margin">26. The Tumult of Apprentices, 26. <hi>July.</hi>
               </note> But ſo it hapned that about <hi>one thouſand Apprentices</hi> wholly unarmed came down two or three howers after with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Petition</hi> of their own to the Houſes: Therein claiming, that <hi>to order the City Militia was the Cities</hi> Birth-right <hi>belonging to them by Charters, confirmed in Parliaments, for defence whereof they had adventured their lives as far as the Army. And deſired the Militia might be put again into the ſame hands in which it was put with the Cities conſent by Ordinance,</hi> May 4.</p>
            <p>Upon reading theſe Petitions the Lords were pleaſed to revoke the Ordinance of <hi>July</hi> 23. and revive that of <hi>May</hi> the 4. by a new Ordinance of <hi>July</hi> 26. which they preſently ſent downe to the Commons for their <hi>conſents,</hi> where ſome of the Apprentices (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming they might have as great an Influence upon the Houſe to obtain <hi>their due,</hi> as the Army in pay of the Parl: had to obtain <hi>more then their due</hi>) in a childiſh heat were over-clamorous to have the Ordinance paſſed, refuſing to let ſome Members paſſe out of the Houſe, or come forth into the Lobby when they were to divide upon the queſtion about it, (ſo ignorant were they of the cuſtoms of the Houſe) which at laſt paſſed in the Affirmative about three of the clock afternoon: and then moſt of the Apprentices de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted quietly into the City. After which,<note n="27" place="margin">27. The Tumult of Apprentices ceaſed, but arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> ſome diſorderly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (very few of them Apprentices) were drawn together and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigated by divers Sectaries and friends of the Army who ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with them (amongſt whom, one <hi>Highland</hi> was obſerved to be all that day very active; who afterwards (26. <hi>Sept.</hi>) delivered a Petition to the Houſe againſt thoſe Members that ſate, and was an Informer and Witneſs examined about the ſaid <hi>Tumult</hi>) ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113968:12"/> about the Commons dore and grew very outragious, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling the <hi>Speaker</hi> to return to the <hi>Chaire</hi> after he had adjour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Houſe: and there kept the Members in untill they had paſſed a Vote, <hi>That the King ſhould come to London to Treat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was cunningly and premeditately contrived, to encreaſe the <hi>ſcandall upon the City;</hi> yet when the Common Councell of <hi>London</hi> heard of this diſorder as they were then ſitting: they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſent down the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> to their reſcue with ſuch ſtrength as they could get ready (their <hi>Militia</hi> being then unſetled by the contradicting Ordinances of the Parliament) who at laſt pacified the Tumult, and ſent the Speaker ſafe home; which was as much as they could do in this intervall of their <hi>Militia,</hi> being the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes own Act.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Lords</hi> adjourned untill the next Friday; the <hi>Commons</hi> but untill the next day. Tueſday morning the <hi>Commons</hi> ſate againe quietly, and after <hi>ſome debate</hi> adjourned untill Friday next, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Lords</hi> had done ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="28" place="margin">28. The Speaker of the Commons complained of a report, that he meant to flie to the Army: yet ran away to the Army.</note>The next day being Wedneſday, the <hi>monthly Faſt,</hi> the <hi>Speaker</hi> and <hi>Members</hi> met in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Church: where the <hi>Speaker</hi> complained (in ſome paſſion) to Sir <hi>Ralph Aſhton</hi> and other Members of a ſcandalous report, raiſed on him in the <hi>City,</hi> as if he intended to deſert the Houſe, and flie to the Army, ſaying, <hi>he ſcorned to do ſuch a baſe, unjuſt, diſhonourable act; but would rather die in his Houſe and Chaire:</hi> which being ſpoken in a time and place of ſo much reverence and devotion, makes many think his ſecret retreat to the Army (the very next day) proceeded not ſo much from his own judgment, as from ſome ſtrong threats from <hi>Cromwell</hi> and <hi>Ireton</hi> (who were the chief <hi>contrivers</hi> of this deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>plot</hi> to divide the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Houſes,</hi> and bring up the <hi>Army</hi> to <hi>enthrall them both</hi>) That if he did not comply with their deſires, they would cauſe the Army to impeach him for couſening the State of many vaſt ſums of mony.</p>
            <p>And truly, I remember I have ſeen an intercepted <hi>Letter,</hi> ſent about the time of his flight, from the Army to <hi>William Lenthall</hi> Speaker,<note n="29" place="margin">29. The City pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt Tumults.</note> without any name ſubſcribed to it, only the two laſt lines were of <hi>John Ruſhworth's</hi> hand; earneſtly importuning him to retire to the Army, with his friends.</p>
            <p>On Thurſday morning early, the newly renewed <hi>Militia</hi> of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113968:12"/> 
               <hi>London,</hi> made publike proteſtation throughout the City and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs, and ſet up printed Tickets at Weſtminſter: <hi>That if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould diſturb either of the two Houſes, or their Members, the Guards ſhould apprehend them, and if reſiſtance were made, kill them:</hi> yet notwithſtanding, the Speaker and his party (carrying the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of their fear in their own conſciences) in the evening of that day ſecretly ſtole away to <hi>Windſor</hi> to the Head quarters.</p>
            <p>Upon Friday morning at leaſt 140.<note n="30" place="margin">30. The Houſes appeare, the Speakers being at the Army.</note> of the Members aſſembled in the Houſe (they that fled being about 40.) whither the Serge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant coming without his <hi>mace,</hi> being asked where the <hi>Speaker was?</hi> anſwered, <hi>he knew not well; that he had not ſeen him that morning, and was told he went a little way out of Town laſt night;</hi> but ſaid, <hi>he expected his return to the Houſe this morning:</hi> after that, being more ſtrictly queſtioned about the <hi>Speaker,</hi> he withdrew himſelf, and would not be found, till the Houſe (after four howrs expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation; and ſending ſome of their Members to the <hi>Speakers houſe,</hi> who brought word from his <hi>ſervants,</hi>
               <note n="31" place="margin">31. New Speakers choſen.</note> that <hi>they conceived he was gone to the Army</hi>) had choſen <hi>a new Speaker,</hi> Mr. <hi>Henry Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and a new <hi>Sergeant,</hi> who procured another <hi>mace.</hi> The like <hi>(mutatis mutandis)</hi> was done by the <hi>Lords,</hi> to prevent diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance and fayler of the Parliament for want of <hi>Speakers</hi> to <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journe</hi> and <hi>continue it;</hi> and take away all ſcruples.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Petition and Engagement of the City</hi> (ſo much aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated by the <hi>Independent</hi> party) it was directed to the <hi>Lord Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, Aldermen,</hi> and <hi>Common Councell</hi> from divers <hi>Citizens,</hi>
               <note n="32" place="margin">32. Petition and engagement of the City.</note> 
               <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders</hi> and <hi>Souldiers,</hi> and was occaſioned by ſome intelligence they had, that <hi>the Army would demand an alteration of the City Militia, in order to a deſigne they had againſt the City.</hi> It was only intended to the <hi>Common Hall,</hi> but never preſented, as the <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers Petition</hi> was to their <hi>Generall,</hi> which being taken notice of by the Parliament as it was in agitation, was ſo much reſented by the Souldiery as to put themſelves into the poſture they are now in (as Lieut. Col. <hi>Lilburne</hi> ſayes in one of his Books) to act no longer by their <hi>Commiſſions,</hi> but by the principles of nature and ſelf-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Nor did the ſaid engagement contain any thing but reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of ſelf-defence in relation to the City: ſo that we cannot ſee what the Army had to declare their ſenſe upon it in their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, 23. <hi>July.</hi> and ſo put a prejudice upon it in the Houſes. I have
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113968:13"/> inſiſted the more particularly upon this <hi>Grand Impoſture</hi> as being the <hi>anvile</hi> upon which they hammered moſt of their ſubſequent deſignes, <hi>violencies</hi> and <hi>illegall accuſations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="33" place="margin">33. Votes paſſed after new Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers choſen.</note>The new Speakers choſen; the <hi>two Houſes proceeded to vote and act,</hi> as a Parliament. And firſt, the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> voted in, the <hi>eleven impeached Members;</hi> next they revive and ſet up again the <hi>Committee of Safety</hi> by Ordinance of both Houſes enabling them to joyne with the <hi>Committee</hi> of the reſtored <hi>City Militia:</hi> giving power by ſeverall Ordinances to them, to Liſt and Raiſe Forces, appoint Commanders and Officers, Iſſue forth Armes and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition for defence of both Houſes and the City againſt all that ſhould invade them: Which votes and preparations for their ſafe defence (warranted by the ſame law of nature as the Armies <hi>papers</hi> affirm) were not paſſed, nor put in execution untill the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my (every day recruited contrary to the Houſes <hi>Orders</hi>) were drawing towards <hi>London,</hi> and had with much ſcorn diſobeyed the Votes and Letter of both Houſes, prohibiting them <hi>to come within thirty miles of London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="34" place="margin">34. Members em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement with the Army.</note>The <hi>Army,</hi> to countenance their Rebellion, draw the <hi>two Speakers and fugitive Members</hi> to ſit in conſultation and paſſe Votes promiſcuouſly with the <hi>Councell of War</hi> in the nature of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and to ſigne an Engagement (<hi>dat.</hi> 4. <hi>August.) to live and die with Sir Tho: Fairfax and the Army under his command;</hi> affirming therein that generally throughout their ſenſe agreeth with the <hi>Declaration</hi> of Sir <hi>Tho: Fairfax,</hi> and his <hi>Councell of War:</hi> ſhewing the grounds of their preſent advance towards the City of <hi>London.</hi> In which <hi>Declaration</hi> the Councell of the Army take upon them, To be <hi>ſupream Judges over the Parliament:</hi> Telling you who of the two Houſes they hold for perſons in whom the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like truſt of the Kingdome remaineth, and by whoſe advice they mean to govern themſelves in managing the weighty affairs of the Kingdome: They declare againſt the late <hi>choice</hi> of a <hi>new Speaker</hi> by ſome Gentlemen at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> and that as things now ſtand there is no free nor legall Parliament ſitting, being through the violence (29. <hi>July</hi>) ſuſpended. That the <hi>Orders</hi> and <hi>Votes, &amp;c.</hi> paſſed 26 <hi>July</hi> laſt, and all ſuch as ſhall paſſe in this Aſſembly of ſome few Lords and Gentlemen at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> are void and null, and ought not to be ſubmitted unto.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113968:13"/>
            <p>Behold here, not only a power <hi>without the Parliament Houſes,</hi> judging of the very <hi>eſſence of a Parliament,</hi> and the validity of their reſolutions, but uſurping to themſelves a <hi>Negative voice,</hi> which they deny to the <hi>King;</hi> and yet a Schiſmaticall faction in the two Houſes complying with them, and betraying and proſtituting the very being, honour, and all the fundamentall Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of this and all future Parliaments, to an Army of Rebells who refuſe to obey their Maſters, and disband.</p>
            <p>This engagement ſo over-leavened the Army, that their brutiſh Generall ſent forth Warrants <hi>to raiſe the Trained Bands</hi> of ſome Counties, to March with him againſt the City and both Houſes: Although Trained Bands are not under pay of the Parliament; and therefore not under <hi>Command of the Generall,</hi> by any Order or Ordinance. But, what will not <hi>a fool in Authority</hi> doe, when he is poſſeſſed by Knaves? Miſerable man! His foolery hath ſo long waited upon <hi>Cromwells</hi> and <hi>Iretons</hi> knavery, that it is not ſafe for him now <hi>to ſee his folly,</hi> and throw by his <hi>Cap with a Bell</hi> and <hi>his Bable.</hi> The Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> dyed ſo opportunely, that many ſuſpected his death was artificiall.</p>
            <p>Yet <hi>the City</hi> were ſo deſirous of Peace,<note n="35" place="margin">35. The City ſend Commiſſioners to the Army, <hi>Fowkes, Gibs,</hi> and <hi>Eaſtweck,</hi> by which they are betrayed.</note> that they <hi>ſent Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners</hi> ſundry times <hi>to the Army</hi> to mediate an Accord; who could obtaine no more equall tearmes of Agreement then that, They ſhould yeild to deſert both Houſes and the impeached Members: Call in their Declaration newly Printed and Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: Relinquiſh their Militia: Deliver up all their Forces and Line of Communication to the Army; together with the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> and all the Magazines &amp; Armes therein: Disband all their Forces: Turn all the Reformado's out of the Line: Withdraw all their Guards from the Houſes: Receive ſuch Guards of Horſe and Foot within the Line, as the Army ſhould appoint to Guard the Houſes: Demoliſh their Workes: And ſuffer the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to March in Triumph through the City, as Conquerers of it and the Parliament, and (as they often give out) of the whole Kingdome: Tearmes which they might have had from the great Turk, had he ſate downe before them and broken ground.</p>
            <p>All which was ſuddainly and diſhonourably yeilded to, and executed accordingly, by ſuch an Army as was not able to fight
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113968:14"/> with one half of the City, had they been united: But they are the <hi>Devills ſeedes-men,</hi> and have ſowen <hi>the Cockle of Hereſie and Schiſme,</hi> ſo aboundantly in City and Country (eſpecially amongſt the more beggerly ſort) that theſe men joyning Principles and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts with the Army, weaken the hands of all opponents. They often brag that they made a civill March, free from Plunder: I Anſwer, they neither durſt, nor could doe otherwiſe: their Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers being ill Armed, and ſo few, that they were not able to keep ſtands in the ſtreets, and keep the Avenues while their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes diſperſed to Plunder. <hi>Charles</hi> 8. with a far greater, and more Victorious hoaſt, durſt not offer violence to the far leſſe City of <hi>Florence</hi> when <hi>Signior Caponi</hi> put an affront upon him in the Town-houſe; Bidding him <hi>beat his Drums, and they would ring their Bells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="36" place="margin">36. The fugitive Members re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned.</note>Upon the 6 of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1647. the <hi>Generall brought the fugitive Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers and Members to the Houſes</hi> with a ſtrong Party, (who might have returned ſooner without a Guard, had not their own crimes &amp; deſignes hindred them) the two Palaces filled with armed guards, double files clean through <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> up the ſtaires to the Houſe of Commons, and ſo through the Courts of Requeſt to the Lords Houſe, and down ſtaires againe into the old Palace. The Souldiers looking ſcornfully upon many Members that had ſate in the abſence of the Speaker, and threatning to cut ſome of their throats. And all things compoſed to ſo ridiculous a terrour, as if they would <hi>beſpeak</hi> (without <hi>ſpeaking</hi>) the abſence of thoſe Members that ſate Placed the Speakers in the Chaires without Vote, out of which they had been juſtly Voted for deſerting their calling; where the Generall was placed in a <hi>Chaire of State</hi> (enough to make a fool of any man that was not fit for it) and received ſpeciall thanks for his ſervice from both Speakers. And in the ſecond place, <hi>a day of thanksgiving</hi> was appointed to God; (I think) for his patience in not ſtriking theſe Atheiſticall Saints with thunder and lightning for making him a ſtale to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated villanies. Here Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> with a breath (and before any man that was not privy to the deſigne could recover out of his amazement) was made <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> of all the Forces and Forts of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales;</hi> to diſpoſe of them at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: Conſtable of the Tower of <hi>London.</hi> The Common Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb facs="tcp:113968:14"/> Voted one monthes gratuity, beſides their pay (the Commons being in good caſe to <hi>give gifts</hi> before they <hi>pay'd debts:</hi>) left to the diſcretion of the Generall to ſet what Guards he pleaſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the two Houſes. Whereby you may perceive in what unequall condition thoſe Members that did not runne away with the Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, doe now ſit; after ſo many reiterated threats of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall againſt them in his printed Papers.</p>
            <p>After this, the <hi>Generall, Lievtenant Generall, and the whole Army,</hi>
               <note n="37" place="margin">37. The Armies March in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph through the City: with other ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Acts.</note> with the Traine of Artillery, <hi>marched through London</hi> in ſo great pomp and triumph, as if they would have the people underſtand that the Authority of the Kingdome (in whoſe hands ſoever it remaines in theſe doubtfull times) muſt ſubmit to the <hi>power of the ſword,</hi> the hilt and handle whereof they hold. They <hi>turne out the Lieutenant of the Tower</hi> without cauſe ſhewne. The conſequencies of theſe two actions were, that immediately the City decayed in Trade above 200000 l. a week; and no more Bullion came to the Mint.</p>
            <p>They diſplace all other Governours, though placed by Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament, and put in men of their owne party; for this incroaching faction will have all in their owne hands. They alter and divide the City of <hi>London,</hi> ſetting up particular Militia's at <hi>Weſtminſter, Southwarke,</hi> and the <hi>Hamlets of the Tower,</hi> that being ſo divided they may be the weaker. Demoliſh the Lines of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication; that the City and Parliament may lie open to Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion when they pleaſe; and fright many more Members from the Houſes with threats, and feare of falſe Impeachments.</p>
            <p>The 11. Impeached Members having leave by Order of the Houſe, and licence of the Speaker ſome to goe beyond Sea; and <hi>Anthony Nicholls</hi> to goe into his owne Country to ſettle his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires: ſome of them (as Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> and M. <hi>Den: Hollis</hi>) were attached upon the Sea; <hi>Nicholls</hi> arreſted upon the way into <hi>Cornewall</hi> by the Army, and deſpightfully uſed; and when the Generall was inclined to free him, <hi>Cromwell</hi> (whoſe <hi>malice</hi> is known to be as unquenchable as his <hi>noſe</hi>) told him he was <hi>a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to the Army.</hi> You ſee now upon whom they meane to fixe the <hi>peoples allegeance,</hi> (for where no <hi>Allegeance</hi> is, there can be no <hi>Treaſon</hi>) and to what purpoſe they have ſince by their 4. Votes (firſt debated between the <hi>Independent Grandees</hi> of the Houſes and Army) laid aſide the King.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113968:15"/>
            <p>Col: <hi>Dirch</hi> formerly imployed for <hi>Ireland</hi> by the Parliament, was impriſoned, and his men mutinyed againſt him by the Army: and Sir <hi>Sam: Luke</hi> reſting quietly in his own houſe, was there ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed upon and carryed Priſoner into the Army.</p>
            <p>All theſe acts of terror were but ſo many Scar-crowes ſet up to fright more Presbyterians from the Houſes, and make the Army maſters of their Votes.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="38" place="margin">38. Proceedings of both Houſes under the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</note>I muſt in the next place fall upon <hi>the proceedings in both Houſes,</hi> acted under <hi>the power</hi> and influence of this all-inſlaving, all-devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Army,</hi> and their engaged party. To attaine the knowledge whereof, I have uſed my utmoſt induſtry and intereſt with many my neere friends and kinſmen ſitting within thoſe walls, hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (when <hi>Kings,</hi> not <hi>Brewers</hi> and <hi>Draymen,</hi> were in power) the walls of publique liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="39" place="margin">39. Ordinance to null and voide all Acts paſſed in abſence of the two renega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Speakers.</note>The Lords that ſate in abſence of the two Speakers (all but the Earle of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> whoſe eaſie diſpoſition made him fit for all companies) found it their ſafeſt courſe to forbeare the Houſe, leaving it to be poſſeſſed by thoſe few Lords that went to, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged with the Army: which engaged Lords ſent to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons for their concurrence to an Ordinance, <hi>To make all Acts, Orders and Ordinances</hi> paſſed from the 26 <hi>July</hi> (when the tumult was upon the Houſes) to the 6. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> following (being the day of the fugitive Members returne) <hi>void</hi> and null <hi>ab initio.</hi> This was five or ſix ſeverall dayes ſeverally and fully debated, as often put to the Queſtion, and carryed in the Negative every time: yet the Lords ſtill renewed the ſame Meſſage to them, beating back their Votes into their throats, and would not acquieſce, but upon every denyall put them againe to roll the ſame ſtone, contrary to the priviledges of the Commons.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="40" place="margin">40. Menaces uſed by the engaged party in the Houſe.</note>The chief Arguments uſed by the engaged party were all groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the Common places of <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>neceſſity:</hi> M. Solicitor threatning if they did not concur, the Lords were reſolved to vindicate the Honour of their Houſe, and ſit no more: they muſt have recourſe to the power of the ſword; the longeſt ſword take all. That they were all engaged to live and die with the Army. They ſhould have a ſad time of it. <hi>Haſterig</hi> uſed the like lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; farther ſaying, Some heads muſt fly off; and he feared the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> would not ſave the Kingdome of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113968:15"/> they muſt look another way for ſafety. They could not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the Army but by declaring all void <hi>ab initio;</hi> and the Lords were ſo far engaged, that no middle way would ſerve. To this was anſwered, that this was an Appeal from the Parliament to the Army. And when theſe and many more threats of as high nature were complained of as deſtructive to the liberty and being of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, the Speaker would take no notice of it. Sir <hi>Henry Vane junior,</hi> Sir <hi>John Evelin junior, Prydeaux, Gourdon, Mildmay, Tho: Scott, Cornel: Holland,</hi> and many more, uſed the like threats.</p>
            <p>Upon the laſt negative (being the fift or ſixth) the Speaker (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving greater enforcements muſt be uſed) pulled a Letter out of his pocket, from the Generall and Generall Councel of the Army,<note n="41" place="margin">41. A threatning Remonſtrance from the Army to the Houſe.</note> (for that was now their ſtyle) pretending he then received it; But it was conceived he received it over night, with directions to conceal it, if the Queſtion had paſſed in the Affirmative. It was accompanyed with a <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> full of villanous language and <hi>threats</hi> againſt <hi>thoſe Members</hi> that ſate while the two Speakers were with the Army: calling them <hi>pretended Members,</hi> Charging them (in generall) with <hi>Treaſon, Treachery, and breach of Truſt:</hi> And proteſted if they ſhall preſume to ſit before they have clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves; that they did not give their aſſents to ſuch and ſuch Votes, they ſhould ſit at their perill, and he would take them as Priſoners of Warre, and try them at a Councell of Warre.</p>
            <p>What King of <hi>England</hi> ever offered ſo great a violence to the fundamentall Priviledges of Parliament, as to deny them the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Voting <hi>I</hi> and <hi>No</hi> freely? Certainly the <hi>little finger</hi> of a <hi>Jack Cade</hi> or a <hi>Wat Tyler,</hi> is far heavier then <hi>the loynes</hi> of any <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many Members were amazed at this Letter, and it was moved, That the Speaker ſhould Command all the Members to meet at the Houſe the next day, and ſhould declare, That they ſhould be ſecured from danger: And that it might be Ordered that no more but the ordinary Guardes ſhould attend the Houſe. But theſe two motions were violently oppoſed with vollies of threats by the aforeſaid parties and others. And after more then two houres debate, the Speaker refuſed to put any queſtion upon them, or any of them; and ſo adjourned to the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113968:16"/> leaving the <hi>Presbyterian Members</hi> to meet at their Perill.</p>
            <p>The next day being Friday, the 20 <hi>Aug.</hi> there was a very thin Aſſembly in the Houſe of Commons; the Houſe having with ſo much violence denyed protection to their Members the day before, made moſt of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> party abſent. Some went over to the <hi>Independent</hi> party: others fate mute. At laſt a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee was appointed preſently to bring in <hi>an Ordinance of Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation;</hi> which was ſuddainly done and paſſed, and is now Printed at the latter end of the ſaid menacing <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> of the Army: a Childe fit to waite upon ſuch a Mother.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="42" place="margin">42. Debate in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of null and voide.</note>Thus was this <hi>Ordinance of null and voyde</hi> gotten (which hath been the cauſe of ſo much danger and trouble to Multitudes of people) by the Lords reiterated breaches upon the Priviledges of the Houſe of Commons. The engaged parties threats within doores: The Armies thundring Letters and Remonſtrance: Their Guardes upon their doores, and a Regiment or two of Horſe in <hi>Hide Parke,</hi> ready to make impreſſions upon the Houſe, in caſe things had not gone to their mindes: diverſe of whoſe Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders walking in the Hall, enquired often how things went, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting they would pull them forth by the Eares if they did not give ſpeedy ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Thus for the <hi>manner</hi> of paſſing that Ordinance; the <hi>matter</hi> of Argument uſed againſt it was (as far as I can hear) to the purpoſe following. It was alledged that the force upon Munday 26 <hi>July,</hi> ended that day, that the next day being Tueſday, the Houſe met quietly and adjourned. That upon Friday following, the Houſes fate quietly all day, and gave their Votes freely and ſo forward; the City having ſufficiently provided for their ſecurity. That this tranfient force upon Munday, could have no influence on the Houſes for the time to come. That the Supream power of no Nation can avoide their owne acts by pretended force. This would make the common People, the Jurors, and Judges to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion all acts done in Parliament, ſince one man can, and may judge of force as well as another. This were to being the Records of the Houſe into diſpute: <hi>Magna Charta</hi> was never gotten nor confirmed but by force; force was threefold: upon one or both Houſes; or upon the King, in giving His Royall Aſſent; neither
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113968:16"/> could plead it, the Parliament is preſumed to conſiſt of ſuch men as dare lay downe their lives for their Country. When the King came with force to demand the 5 Members; when the City came downe crying for Juſtice againſt the Earl of <hi>Strafford;</hi> when the women came down crying for Peace; when the Reformado's came down in a much more dangerous Tumult then this of the unarmed Prentices; yet the Houſes continued ſitting and Acting, and none of their Acts were nullified. That to make their Acts, Orders and Ordinances voide <hi>ab initio,</hi> would draw many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men who had acted under them into danger of their lives and fortunes, who had no Authority to diſpute the validity of our Votes: we muſt therefore give them power to diſpute our acts hereafter upon matter of fact; for to tie men to unlimited and undiſputable obedience to our Votes, and yet to puniſh them for obeying whenſoever we ſhall pleaſe to declare our acts voide, <hi>ab initio,</hi> is contrary to all reaſon. If to act upon ſuch Ordinances were criminall, it was more criminall in thoſe that made them. And who ſhall be judges of thoſe that made them? Not the Members that went to the Army; They are parties pre-ingaged to live and die with the Army; and have approved the <hi>Armies Declaration,</hi> calling thoſe that ſate, <hi>a few Lords and Gentlemen, and no Parliament:</hi> they have joyned with a power out of the Houſes to give a Law to, and put an engagement upon both Houſes; a preſident never heard of before, of moſt dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, it takes away the liberty of giving <hi>I</hi> and <hi>No</hi> freely, being the very life of Parliaments: If all done under an actuall force be voide, it is queſtionable whether all hath been done this 4 or 5 years be not voide; and whether His Majeſties Royall Aſſent to ſome good Bils paſſed this Parliament, may not be ſaid to have been extorted by force: if the Kings Party prevaile, they will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare this Parliament voide, upon the ground your ſelves have laid. 1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. That King urged the Parliament to make voide <hi>ab initio,</hi> all Acts paſſed <hi>Rich.</hi> 3. which they refuſed upon this ground: That then they ſhould make all that had Acted in obedience to them lyable to puniſhment, only they repealed thoſe Acts.</p>
            <p>The debate upon this <hi>Ordinance of null and voyde,</hi> held from Munday 9 of <hi>Aug.</hi> to the 20 <hi>Aug.</hi> (when it was paſſed) but not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113968:17"/> without ſome interloaping debates of ſomething a different na-nature, yet all looking the ſame way: occaſioned by <hi>Meſſages</hi> from the Lords: Namely, once upon a Meſſage from them, The ſaid <hi>Declaration,</hi> from Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> and his Army,<note n="43" place="margin">43. The Lords Meſſage to the Commons to approve the Declaration of the Army.</note> concerning their <hi>advance to London</hi> was read &amp; debated in groſſe, whether the <hi>Commons</hi> ſhould concur with the <hi>Lords</hi> in approving it? But almoſt all but the engaged Party and their Penſioners diſtaſted it, it was laid by without any queſtion put, leſt it ſhould prove dangerous to put a Negative upon their Maſters of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. Yet many menaces (according to cuſtome) were uſed by the engaged party to get it paſſed; <hi>Haſterig</hi> affirming that thoſe Gentlemen that ſate and voted for a <hi>Committee of ſafety,</hi>
               <note n="44" place="margin">44. The Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of ſafety.</note> and the Kings comming to <hi>London,</hi> did drive on the deſigne of the <hi>City proteſtation</hi> and engagement. To which was Anſwered, That the Committee of ſafety was not then newly erected by thoſe which ſate, but the old Committee revived by that Vote, which had been long ſince erected in a full &amp; free Parliament, when the Army firſt mutinyed and threatned to March to <hi>London:</hi> and for the ſame ends; Defence of Parliament and City. And for the Kings comming to <hi>London,</hi> it was Voted only to get Him out of the power of the Army; as formerly in a full and free Parliament he had been voted to <hi>Richmond</hi> for the ſame reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="45" place="margin">45. A Committee to examine the Tumult.</note>Upon another Meſſage from the Lords, the Commons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred in an Ordinance to erect a <hi>Committee of Examinations</hi> to inquire into, and examine the <hi>City Petition, engagement, and the force upon the Houſes</hi> 26 <hi>July,</hi> and all endeavours to raiſe any forces,<note n="46" place="margin">46. A Sub-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſelected to examine the Tumult.</note> &amp;c. This Committee conſiſted of 22 Commons beſides Lords, almoſt all of them Members engaged with the Army: but becauſe there were ſome three or four Presbyterians gotten in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, to ſhut theſe <hi>Canaanites</hi> forth, that the Godly, the true ſeed of <hi>Iſrael</hi> might ſhuffle the Cardes according to their owne minde, the 13 <hi>Aug.</hi> after (upon another Meſſage from the Lords) there was a <hi>Sub-committee of Secrecy,</hi> named out of this grand Committee of Examinations, to examine upon Oath. The perſons were, the Earl of <hi>Denbigh</hi> and <hi>Mulgrave,</hi> Lord <hi>Gray</hi> of <hi>Wark,</hi> Lord <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Eſcrig,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Haſterig,</hi> Mr. Solicitor, <hi>Gourdon, Miles Corbet,</hi> Alderman <hi>Pennington, Allen, Edwards,</hi> Col: <hi>Ven,</hi> or any three of them. All perſons engaged to live and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113968:17"/> die with the Army, and now appointed to make a clandeſtine ſcrutiny, and ſearch into the lives and Actions of the <hi>Preſbyterian party</hi> that ſate in Parliament doing their duty, when the engaged party fled to the Army, and brought them up in hoſtile manner againſt them.</p>
            <p>The unreaſonableneſſe of this way of proceeding was much urged;<note n="47" place="margin">47. Debate upon the paſſing the Committee of Secret exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</note> and farther alleaged that it was neither <hi>conſonant to the Cuſtomes of the Houſe,</hi> nor unto <hi>common reaſon,</hi> That a <hi>Sub-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee</hi> ſhould be choſen out of the <hi>Grand Committee of examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> with more power then the Grand Committee it ſelf had, and excluding the reſt of the Committee, under the pretence of <hi>ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</hi> Beſides, it was againſt the priviledge of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, that the Lords ſhould nominate the Commons in that Sub-committee as well as their own Members. But the <hi>Independent Grandees</hi> would have it paſſe. Breach of Priviledge, and all other conſiderations are eaſily ſwallowed when they are ſubſervient to their preſent deſignes.</p>
            <p>The party engaged were reſolved to be <hi>Examiners, Informers,</hi>
               <note n="48" place="margin">48. The manner of proſecution and proceeding upon the Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult.</note> and <hi>witneſſes,</hi> as well as <hi>parties,</hi> (ſo active was their malice) and had ſo well packed the Cardes, that eight or nine Schiſmaticall Lords engaged likewiſe with them, and the Army ſhould be judges of the <hi>Presbyterian party</hi> that ſate in abſence of the two Speakers, the better to give the two Houſes a through Purge, and make them of the ſame complexion with the Army: without which they had no hopes to divide the power and profit of the Land be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween themſelves by 10000. l. 20000. l. in a morning ſhared amongſt the godly; and to make the whole Kingdom to be <hi>Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> hewers of wood, and drawers of water to the faithfull.</p>
            <p>In order to the playing of this game,<note n="49" place="margin">49. <hi>Miles Corbet</hi> makes report of Examinations taken at the cloſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Firſt, againſt the Committee of Safety.</note> 
               <hi>Miles Corbet</hi> (Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to that <hi>State-puppet-play</hi> behinde the curtain, commonly called <hi>The cloſe Committee of examinations</hi>) upon the 3. <hi>Septemb.</hi> ſtood up and <hi>began his Report</hi> from that <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> ſaying, he would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the <hi>Committee of ſafety,</hi> wherein many Members were concerned; and it was neceſſary to purge the Houſes firſt. But farther ſaid, he would ſuppreſſe the Nantes of many of his Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, becauſe the Depoſitions he ſhould report were but <hi>prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory examinations,</hi> and it would be for ſervice of the State to conceal their names.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113968:18"/>
            <p>He firſt produced many Warrants ſigned at the <hi>Committee of Safety</hi> by the Earles of <hi>Pembroke, Suffolke, Middleſex, Lincolne,</hi> Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> of <hi>Parham, Maynard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> Sir <hi>Phil: Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> Mr. <hi>Long,</hi> Mr. <hi>Nicholls,</hi> Sir <hi>William Lewes,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baynton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, <hi>Corbet</hi> reported he had a Witneſſe who depoſed that a Gentleman with a <hi>red head</hi> had ſigned many Warrants, ſuppoſed to be Mr. <hi>Edward Baynton:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Againſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Baynton.</hi>
               </note> at length after much wyer-drawing of the buſineſſe, one Warrant was ſhewn to Mr. <hi>Baynton,</hi> which he confeſſed to be his hand. And preſently <hi>Haſlerigge</hi> moved that Mr. <hi>Baynton</hi> might forthwith Anſwer: againſt which was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, That ſince theſe were but preparatory examinations, not legall proofs, no man was bound to anſwer them: otherwiſe a man ſhall be put to as many ſeverall anſwers as ſeverall new mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Charge come in againſt him, and ſhall day by day be liable to new vexations, and never know when he hath cleered himſelf. But <hi>Corbet</hi> (who of an Examiner was now become the <hi>Kings</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitor, or Advocate Criminall) moved to proceed to judgment againſt him: but firſt to ask him ſome preparatory queſtions. But it was anſwered, that it was illegall to ſqueeſe examinations out of a mans own mouth; neither was a man bound to anſwer, where his words may condemn, but not abſolve hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: for ſo much as depends upon the teſtimony of Witneſſes againſt this Gentleman, you cannot proceed unleſſe he be by, and have liberty to put croſſe queſtions to the Witneſſes. It is alleaged, Warrants were ſigned, and all done in relation to a new war. It is anſwered, it was done in order to ſelf-defence (allowable by the Lawes.) Long before this occaſion, when the Army firſt mutinied and threatned to march up to <hi>London,</hi> and uſe ſuch extraordinary means againſt the <hi>Parliament and City</hi> as God had put into their hands, you then in a full and free Parliament appointed a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of ſafety for your defence, who ſate and acted. This Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee was but the ſame revived, and upon the like or worſe threats and menaces, as by the many printed Papers from the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my will appear; you have no Teſtimony againſt this Gentleman by name, but only a Character of his haire: and for ſigning the Warrant confeſſed by himſelf he is acquitted by the <hi>Proviſo</hi> of the Ordinance, 20. <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, which excepteth only ſuch as acted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113968:18"/> upon the force, But when the <hi>Committee of ſafety</hi> was revived, the Parliament was freer from force then it is how. Mr. <hi>Baynton</hi> notwithſtanding was adjudged to be ſuſpended the Houſe during pleaſure of the Houſe, which is as much as to ſay, So long as the Tyranny of this domineering Faction laſteth.</p>
            <p>The 4.<note place="margin">Againſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Walker.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Sept. Corbet</hi> reported he had a Witneſſe (but named him not, becauſe they were but preparatory examinations) who depoſed that an elderly Gentleman of low ſtature, in a gray ſuit, with a little Stick in his hand, came forth of the Houſe into the Lobby when the Tumult was at the Parliament dore, and whiſpered ſome of the Apprentices in the eare, and encouraged them, (ſuppoſed to be Mr. <hi>Walker.</hi>) Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> denied he ſpake then with any man in the <hi>Lobby,</hi> or ſaw any face that he knew there; and ſo neglected the buſineſſe as a thing not conſiderable. But the next day <hi>Corbet</hi> moved that Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> might be orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to put on his gray Suite againe and appeare before the Cloſe Committee, and the Witneſſe, who ſaith he knoweth him againe if he ſee him. I heare Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> deſired to know (ſeeing the Witneſſe had not named him) by what authority the Examiners ſhould take ſuch a Depoſition, and make application thereof to him: and ſeeing there were many Gentlemen in the Houſe that day with whom that Character agreed as well as with himſelf, why the Reporter did not move that all to whom that Character was applyable might be put to that teſt as well as himſelfe, but ſingled him out for a marke to ſhoot at: complaining he was not ignorant out of what Quiver this Arrow came: he had beene threatned with a Revenge by ſome of that Cloſe Committee, and had other enemies amongſt them, that could bite without bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. He told them that yeſterday Mr. <hi>Corbet</hi> Reported that the ſuppoſed old man whiſpered, &amp;c. but deſired thoſe that were then in the Houſe to call to mind that the noiſe was then ſo great in the <hi>Lobby</hi> that no whiſper, nay the lowdeſt words he was able to ſpeak could not be heard. Then <hi>Corbet</hi> changed his Tale, ſaying, the words were, What you doe, doe quickly: and were ſpoken aloud: and ſaid, the Character agreed beſt with Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> for that the Deponent ſaid, the Gentleman was a Leane meager man.</p>
            <p>Here Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> deſired the Houſe to take notice that the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113968:19"/> Reporter had twice varyed his Report. 1. In the words ſpoken, from a <hi>whiſper</hi> to <hi>lowd ſpeaking.</hi> 2. In the Character inlarged with the words <hi>leane</hi> and <hi>meager.</hi> Here is Hayle-ſhot provided, if one miſſe, the other muſt hit; Yet with this addition, there were divers in the Houſe with whom the Character agreed as well as with himſelf. And by the incivility of his words, it ſhould ſeem the Witneſſe is a man of no breeding: wherefore he deſired to hear his Name, that he might enquire of his credit and repute. If the Reporter thinks he may be practiſed, he doth not think him a man of honeſty: and then he had more cauſe to ſuſpect him. He farther complained, that to make Hue and Cry after him (as it were upon freſh ſuite) upon a character of his perſon and cloths five or ſix weeks after the ſuppoſed fact, (he never having abſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe one day from the Houſe) favoured too much of a party overſwayed with malice and Revenge.</p>
            <p>Your <hi>cloſe Committee of examinations</hi> carry on buſineſſes ſo in the darke (being parties ingaged with the Army, and not ſworne to be true in their office) that no man can ſee how to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or how he is dealt with, or when he is free from trouble and danger: It ſeems we are here called <hi>ex tempore</hi> to anſwer for our lives, <hi>ore tenus;</hi> And our <hi>Accuſation</hi> beginneth with the <hi>exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> of our perſons: to make us ſtate a <hi>Charge</hi> againſt our ſelves, to <hi>betray</hi> our ſelves, and <hi>cut</hi> our own throats with our tongues, contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> and all thoſe laws of God and man, which in the KING'S time, were in uſe. And no Witneſſes are produced, nor ſo much as named: me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks therefore we are compelled to play at <hi>blind-man-bough</hi> for our lives, not ſeeing who ſtrikes us. You have the moſt ſummary way of hanging one another that ever I ſaw; It is a kind of Star-Chamber proceeeding in matter of life and death; your <hi>ſecret examinations</hi> ſavour ſo much of the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> and of the <hi>Councel of troubles</hi> erected by the Duked' <hi>Alva</hi> in the <hi>Low-countries</hi> (called <hi>Concilium Sanguinis</hi>) that they can never agree with the <hi>laws and nature</hi> of <hi>our Nation:</hi> If our Kings ſhall imitate you hereafter, they will be the greateſt Tyrants in the world. Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and priviledges of Court, derogating from the common rules of Law, and practice of the land, are but curtains drawn before oppreſſion and tyranny to dazle mens eyes. Give me leave
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113968:19"/> to tell you that I have ſerved you faithfully from the beginning, and have taken as much paines, and run as many hazards as moſt men in your ſervice, wherein I have loſt my health and above 7000l. of my Eſtate, without one penny compenſation, as other men have had, nor have I laid my hands upon any mans mony or goods, or had any gainfull imployment from you: I contented my ſelf to ſerve my Country <hi>gratis:</hi> and with ſome little Honour I had gotten thereby; whereby, you have now Robbed me, by a Roaving accuſation ſhot at Random at me. Had I cheated the State of 40000l. or 50000l. peradventure I might have beene thought a godly, confiding man, of right principles, and have had 10000l. given me for my paines. <hi>Sir,</hi> you have heard the voice of a Free-man (not of a Slave) that dares keep his firſt principles, Religion, Lawes, and juſt Liberties whoſoever layes them aſide; and proteſt againſt Tyranny and Oppreſſion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he finds it, whether in the Government of <hi>one</hi> or <hi>many.</hi> You may murder me by the Sword of Juſtice, but you cannot hurt me: but deliver me from the evills to come. Nor ſhall I be unwilling to ſuffer a Goale-delivery of my ſoul from the priſon of my body when I am called to it.</p>
            <p>When Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> had done his defence, the debate followed, much to this purpoſe, <hi>That to order him to appear in his Gray ſuite before the cloſe Committee and Witneſſe was illegall, and againſt the Lawes and Liberties of the Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It is to help another to accuſe himſelf; which is all one as if he did accuſe himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>To bid a Witneſſe look upon a man</hi> (after he is engaged to name ſome body) <hi>is to prompt him to go no farther then the party ſhewed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>A Witneſſe ought not to be twice examined againſt a man.</hi> That is, <hi>to draw him on by degrees to ſwear home, and to mend in his ſecond Depoſition what fell ſhort in his firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>If the Witneſſe firſt depoſe to the matter, not naming the party, and five or ſix weeks after declare the Perſon, without oath, this is no Depoſition, and if the Oath be renewed the Witnes is twice examined.</hi> So the buſineſſe was laid by, and <hi>Corbet</hi> allowed to ſhew Mr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> caſually as he could meet with him to his witneſſe, which was (in a manner) to draw dry foot after him with his bloud-hound.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:113968:20"/>
            <p>I was the more curious in gathering the circumſtances of this buſineſſe out of the reports of many ſeverall men, in regard of the rareneſſe of the caſe, and the exquiſiteneſſe of the malice with which it was proſecuted. And it ſeemed to me the more admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, becauſe I heare generally that Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> hath alwaies been oppoſite to all parties and factions, both <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> and <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent,</hi> upon whom he looks as the common diſturbers both of Church and Common-wealth, and enemies of peace. Nor could he ever be perſwaded to be at any of their <hi>Junto's</hi> or ſecret mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; and therefore it is not probable he ſhould ſuddenly and in the open view of the Houſe go forth and engage with a company of ſilly unarmed Apprentice Boyes. But I heare they cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure his ſeverity, nor he their knavery. What will not the malice of a deſperate <hi>Anabaptiſticall</hi> faction attempt? they have long <hi>ſported</hi> in the bloud and treaſure of the land, as the <hi>Leviathan</hi> doth in the waters: and do now keep up a numerous Army to carry on thoſe deſignes by <hi>force,</hi> which they can no longer make good by <hi>fraud.</hi> All <hi>England</hi> is become as <hi>Munster</hi> was, and our <hi>Grandees</hi> ſutable to <hi>John of Leyden,</hi> and <hi>Knipperdolling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Againſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Recorder <hi>Glyn.</hi>
               </note>The next report <hi>Corbet</hi> made concerning Mr. Recorder <hi>Glyn.</hi> The chief things objected were, <hi>That he had frequented the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Councell, the Committees of the Militia, and ſafety, more then he was w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt to doe: That he was ſilent and made no oppoſition: And that he gave thanks to the Apprentices when they delivered their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to the City, offering their help for defence thereof against whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Recorder anſwered, <hi>the Charge was long, and his memory ſhort: He deſired time to examine his memory, concerning the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of time, place, perſons, and other matters; and that he might examine witneſſes for clearing his innocency.</hi> But his Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors (hoping to do more good upon him by way of ſurpriſe, then in a deliberate and legall way of proceeding) put him upon it to anſwer <hi>ex tempore.</hi> He confeſſed and avoided ſome things, but denied the moſt materiall. He denied he was more frequent at their meetings then ordinary. For his ſilence, he alleaged he was but the Cities ſervant and had no voice amongſt them, but when his opinion was demanded: That he gave thanks to the Apprentices as a ſervant by command, yet had mixed ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113968:20"/> and Reprehenſions in ſpeech to them.</p>
            <p>So the Recorder withdrew. And preſently <hi>Haſterig</hi> (according to his cuſtome) moved judgement might be given againſt him. To which was anſwered, that the Recorder denyed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> principall parts of his Charge; and offered proofes by witneſſes: you muſt give him that leave, or take all parts of his ſpeech for granted; as well what makes for him, as againſt him. Two or three dayes more will make this buſineſſe ripe for judgement: let him have one judgement for all. If you judge him now to be expelled the Houſe, he is already forejudged, &amp; that will be a leading caſe to a farther judgement: For who dares acquit where you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned? A man ought to be but once judged upon one accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The diſhonour of expulſion is a puniſhment exceeding death. If you judge now upon one part of the Accuſation, and hereafter upon another part of the Accuſation, he will be twice condemned upon one Accuſation. And ſhall never know when he hath ſatiſfied the Law; an endleſſe vexation.</p>
            <p>Yet <hi>Haſterig</hi> moved he might receive judgement now, for what was already proved or confeſſed, to be expelled the Houſe; (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Lords went on without obſtruction in their buſineſſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had purged their Houſe) and that he might be farther impeached hereafter upon farther hearing. So he was adjudged to be diſcharged the Houſe, committed to the Tower, and further impeached hereafter.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Maynard</hi> the ſame day was called to Anſwer.<note place="margin">Againſt Sir <hi>John Maynard.</hi>
               </note> He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired a Copy of his Charge, with leave to Anſwer in writing by advice of Councell, as the 11 Members formerly did: To exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine witneſſes on his part, and croſſe examine their witneſſes.</p>
            <p>But theſe requeſts were denye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and he Commanded to anſwer <hi>ex tempore.</hi> He gave no particular Anſwer, but denyed all in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall: as Col: <hi>Pride</hi> (whom he cited for his Preſident) had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly done at their Barre. He was adjudged to be diſcharged the Houſe, committed to the Tower, and farther impeached. The like for Commiſſary Generall <hi>Copley</hi> whoſe caſe differed little.</p>
            <p>The 8 of <hi>Sept.</hi> the Earl of <hi>Suffolke, Lincolne, Middleſex,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Againſt the 7 Lords.</note> the Lords <hi>Barkley, Willoughby, Hunſdon,</hi> and <hi>Maynard</hi> were impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched of High Treaſon, in the name of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:113968:21"/> for levying war againſt the King, Parliament, and Kingdom. The Earle of <hi>Pembroke</hi> (then ſent to <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> with the <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions</hi> on purpoſe to avoid the ſtorm) was omitted untill Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day following, and ſo had the favour to be thought not worth remembring. Sir <hi>John Evelyn</hi> the younger ſent up to the Lords with the <hi>Impeachment,</hi> and a deſire they might be <hi>committed.</hi> They were committed to the <hi>Black Rodde.</hi> And ſo the engaged Lords had their Houſe to themſelves according to their deſires.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="50" place="margin">50. Schiſmaticall Petitions.</note>The 14. <hi>Sept.</hi> a Petition from divers <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> in <hi>Eſſex</hi> came to the Houſes, bearing this Title, <hi>To the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, diſtinct from thoſe Lords and Commons that ſate in abſence of the two Speakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. <hi>Sept.</hi> a Petition from divers <hi>Sectaries</hi> of <hi>Oxfordſh: Bucks: Berkeſh:</hi> was delivered the Houſe againſt diverſe <hi>Members</hi> ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the Houſe, <hi>enemies to God and Godlineſſe, enemies to the Kingdome, &amp;c. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers of Parliamentary Authority, who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to bring in the King upon His owne Tearmes.</hi> They deſired <hi>a free Parliament, and that</hi> (according to the deſires of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my) <hi>thoſe that ſate when the Parliament was ſuſpended in abſence of the two Speakers, might be removed:</hi> there was a clauſe <hi>againſt Tythes, &amp;c.</hi> in it. Such another Petition came but the day before from <hi>Southwarke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Petitions were all penned by the engaged party of the Houſes and Army, and ſent abroad by Agitators to get ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.<note place="margin">The ayme of theſe Petitions.</note> The deſigne was to put the two parties in the Houſe into <hi>heights one againſt another,</hi> to make the <hi>leſſer party</hi> in the Houſe (<hi>viz.</hi> the engaged party but 59) to <hi>expell the greater party</hi> being above 140. whereby the Houſe might be low and baſe in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the people, and no Parliament, and ſo leave all to the power of the Sword. The Army daily recruiting, and thereby giving hopes to all looſe people, that the Army ſhould be their common Receptacle, as the Sea is the common Receptacle of all waters; becauſe thoſe who had no hope to be Members of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament might become Members of this Army. Beſides their plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible way of prompting the people to petition <hi>againſt Tythes, Encloſures, and Copy hold fines uncertain,</hi> was to encourage them to ſide with the Army againſt all the <hi>Nobility, Gentry, and Clergy of the hand,</hi> (from whom the Army did moſt fear an oppoſition)
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113968:21"/> and to deſtroy <hi>Monarchy</hi> it ſelf: ſince it is impoſſible for any Prince, to be a King only of Beggers, Tinkers, and Coblers.</p>
            <p>But theſe interloping diſcourſes omitted, let us again return to theſe prodigious <hi>Impeachments.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Againſt the Lord Mayor, Aldermen and Citizens.</note> The next in order comes in <hi>the Lord Mayor, Aldermen,</hi> and <hi>Citizens,</hi> with whom ſhort work was made. Impeachments were ſent up <hi>to the Lords</hi> againſt them, and they ſent to the <hi>Tower,</hi> upon a bare <hi>report</hi> of the Inquiſitor Generall <hi>Corbet,</hi> and the reading of ſome depoſitions, the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes names</hi> for the moſt part <hi>concealed,</hi> and none of them ſo much as called to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons Bar</hi> to ſee what they could ſay for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> 29. <hi>chap.</hi> and contrary to 28 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. enacting, <hi>that no man ſhall be put out of his Land, &amp;c. nor taken, nor Impriſoned, &amp;c. nor put to death, &amp;c. without being brought to anſwer by due proceſſe of Law.</hi> That is according to the <hi>Stat.</hi> 42 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>ch.</hi> 3. <hi>That no man be brought to anſwer without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment before Juſtices, or matter of Record, or by due proceſs, or writ originall, according to the old Law of the Land:</hi> not according to new invented Articles of impeachment, but according to thoſe Laws that were well known, and old in <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. time: ſee <hi>Stat.</hi> 37 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>ch.</hi> 12. 6 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>ch.</hi> 11. and the <hi>Stat.</hi> 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. ſaith, <hi>no man ſhall be taken by Petition or ſugeſtion made to the King, or his Councell, &amp;c.</hi> and the Houſe of Peers is no more but the Kings Councell, as anon I ſhall make evident.</p>
            <p>It was moved by divers that theſe Gent:<note n="51" place="margin">51. Arguments againſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lords.</note> might be Tried accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law at the <hi>Kings Bench</hi> by a Jury of twelve men <hi>de vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neto,</hi> their Peers and equalls to judge of matter of fact: alleaging that the Common Law was the <hi>Birthright of all the free people of England:</hi> which was one of the <hi>three Principles</hi> for which the Parl: ſo often declared in print that they fought, and for defence wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they had entred into a <hi>Covenant, with their hands lifted up to God:</hi> the other <hi>two principles</hi> were <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Lords were not Peers to the Commoners: At the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law they ſhall have ſworn Judges for matter of Law, of whom they may aske queſtions in doubtfull poynts, nor can they be Judges in their own caſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>They have ſworn Jurors of the neighbourhood for matters of fact, whom they may challenge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The known Laws and Statutes for rules to judge by, which in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113968:22"/> caſe of Treaſon is the</hi> Stat. 25 Edw. 3. <hi>you cannot Vote nor declare a new Treaſon:</hi> And if you could, <hi>to do it</hi> ex poſt facto, <hi>is contrary to all rules of juſtice:</hi> The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Sin is a breach of a Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement</hi> (or Law:) <hi>I had not known ſin but by the Law:</hi> the Law therefore moſt go before the Sin.</p>
            <p n="4">4. At the Common Law, <hi>They have Witneſſes openly and newly examined upon oath before the Accuſed's face, who may except againſt them, and croſs examine them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Even in Star Chamber and Chauncery</hi> (where only hearings are upon Teſtimonies) <hi>the Examiners are ſworn Officers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>A man hath but one Tryall and Judgment, upon one accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> ſo that he knows when he hath ſatisfied the Law.</p>
            <p>In this way of proceeding, all theſe neceſſary legalities are laid by: and theſe Gentlemen have not ſo much fair play for their Lives and Eſtates as <hi>Naboth</hi> had for his Vineyard: he had all the <hi>formalities</hi> of the law: yea, he had <hi>law it ſelf:</hi> yet he had <hi>not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice:</hi> becauſe they were the ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> that were ſet before him: what ſhall we conceive theſe Witneſſes are that do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear? nay, whoſe very names are concealed? yet <hi>Naboth</hi> was murdered by the ſword of Juſtice: for the honour of Parliaments give not the people cauſe to ſuſpect, theſe Gentlemen ſhall be ſo too: <hi>non recurrendum ad extraordinaria, quando fieri poteſt per or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all this was but to charme a deafe Adder: the nine or ten <hi>engaged Lords</hi> that then poſſeſſed the Houſe, were thought to be fitter then a <hi>Jury of Middleſex</hi> to make work for the hang-man,<note n="52" place="margin">52. Arguments proving the Lords to have no power of Iudicature over the Commons.</note> and yet they have <hi>no Judicature over the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons:</hi> as appears by the the preſident of Sir <hi>Simon de Berisforde, William Taylboys,</hi> and the City of <hi>Cambridge.</hi> Note that one preſident againſt the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of a Court is more valued then a hundred for it: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Court cannot be ſuppoſed ignorant of the Law, and its own rights; but a particular man or client may: ſee Sir <hi>John Maynard's Royall quarrell, and his Laws ſubverſion:</hi> Lieut. Col. <hi>Lilburne's whip for the preſent Houſe of Lords:</hi> and Judge <hi>Jenkins Remonstrance to the Lords and Commons of the two Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> dated 21. <hi>Febr.</hi> 1647. As for the caſes of <hi>Weſton, Gomenes</hi> and <hi>Hall,</hi> (cited by Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi>) they were for facts done beyond Sea, and before the <hi>Stat.</hi> 1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>ch.</hi> 14. whereof the Common
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113968:22"/> Law could then have no conuſance: &amp; therefore an extraordinary way of proceeding before the Lords was requiſite, and by the Kings ſpeciall Authority it was done, without which, (I dare boldly affirme) the Lords have no Judicature at all:<note n="53" place="margin">53. The Houſe of Peers no Court of Iudicature at at all properly, and <hi>per ſe.</hi>
               </note> which thus I make appear.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The King by delivering the Great Seale to the <hi>Lord Keeper,</hi> makes him <hi>Keeper of his Conſcience</hi> for matter of equity. By his <hi>Brevia patentia</hi> to the <hi>Judges of the two Benches, and the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer,</hi> the King makes them <hi>adminiſtrators and Interpreters of his Lawes:</hi> But he never truſts any but himſelf with the power of pardoning and diſpenſing with the rigour of the Law in Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall caſes: And though the Lord Keeper is Speaker of the Lords Houſe of Court, yet he is no Member of the Lords Houſe <hi>virtute officii:</hi> The Judges are not Members, but Aſſiſtants only: So that no man in the Houſe of Peers, as he is ſimply a Peere, is truſted by the King either with diſpenſation of law, or equity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When a Peer of Parliament, or any man elſe is tried before the Lords in Parliament criminally, he cannot be tried by his Peers only, becauſe in acts of Judicature, there muſt be a Judge ſuperior, who muſt have his inferiors miniſteriall to him: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Triall of the Earle of <hi>Strafford</hi> (as in all other Trialls upon life and death, in the Lords Houſe) the King grants his Commiſſion to a <hi>Lord High Steward</hi> to ſit as Judge, and the reſt of the Lords are but in the nature of Jurors. So that it is the <hi>Kings Commiſſion</hi> that authoriſeth and diſtinguiſheth them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When a <hi>Writ of Error</hi> iſſueth out of the Chauncery to the Houſe of Peers, they derive their Authority meerly from that Writ.</p>
            <p>For the three Reaſons aforeſaid, The <hi>Houſe of Peers</hi> is no Court of Judicature at all without the <hi>Kings ſpeciall Authority</hi> granted to them either by his <hi>Writ.</hi> or his <hi>Commiſſion.</hi> And the Lords by their <hi>four Votes</hi> having denied all farther addreſſe or application to the King, have cut off from themſelves that fountaine from which they derive all their power: And all Trialls by Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion muſt be upon Bils, or Acts of Attainder, not by <hi>Articles of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment;</hi> a way never heard of before this Parliament, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented to carry on the deſignes of a reſtleſſe impetuous Faction: Had the Faction had but ſo much wit as to try thoſe Gentlemen
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113968:23"/> by Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer and Terminer,</hi> before Sergeant <hi>Wild,</hi> he would have borrowed a point of law to hang a hundred of them for his own preferment.</p>
            <p>Obſerve that almoſt all the caſes cited by Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> concerning the Peers Trialls of Commiſſioners were authorized by the King, upon the ſpeciall inſtance of the Houſe of Commons; As for the Houſe of Commons they never pretended to any power of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, and have not ſo much authority as to adminiſter an oath, which every Court of Pye-pouldres hath.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="54" place="margin">54. Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nke im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachments dorment.</note>But this way of triall before the pre-ingaged Lords, and upon <hi>Articles of Impeachment</hi> (which they keep by them of all ſorts and ſizes fit for every man, as in <hi>Birchin-lane</hi> they have ſuites rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy made to fit every body) was the apter meanes to bring thoſe men to death whom they feared living: had not a doubt of the Scots comming in taught them more moderation, then their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is uſually acquainted with; and to fright away, or (at leaſt) put to ſilence the reſt of the <hi>Members</hi> with fear of having their names put into <hi>blank Impeachments.</hi> And that it might be ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended; <hi>Miles Corbet</hi> moved openly in the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons that they ſhould proceed with the Impeachments which were ready, nothing wanted but to fill up the Blanks, they might put in what names they pleaſed. This <hi>Inquiſitor generall,</hi> this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue to the Hang-man that looks more like a hang-man then the Hang-man himſelf, hath ſince gotten the rich office of <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Chauncery,</hi> as a reward for his double diligence: Oh, Sergeant <hi>Wilde</hi> and Mr. <hi>Steele</hi> deſpair not of a reward.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="55" place="margin">55. Eſtabliſhment for the Army.</note>Friday, 17. <hi>Sept.</hi> the advice of Sir <hi>Tho: Fairfax</hi> and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of War was read in the Houſe of Commons, <hi>what ſtanding Forces</hi> they thought fit to be kept up in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> and <hi>what Garriſons.</hi> Alſo <hi>what Forces to ſend for Ireland;</hi> namely, for <hi>Ireland,</hi> 6000 Foot, and 2400 Horſe, out of the ſupernumerary looſe forces, being no part of the Army; And for <hi>England,</hi> upon eſtabliſhed pay, 18000 Foot at 8<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>per diem.</hi> 7200 Horſe at 2<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. <hi>per diem</hi> each Trouper; 1000 Dragoones, and 200 Firelocks. Traine of Artillery, Armes and Ammunition, to be ſupplied. The Foot to be kept in Garriſons, yet ſo that 6000 may be readily drawn, into the field.</p>
            <p>The Independent party argued, That the Army were unwilling
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113968:23"/> to goe for <hi>Ireland,</hi> pretending their engagement to the contrary; if you divide or disband any part of your Army, they will ſuſpect you have taken up your old reſolutions againſt them, to disband the whole Army: It is now no time to diſcontent them, when the Kings Anſwer to your Propoſitions tends to divide you and your Army, and the people are generally diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to you.</p>
            <p>The Presbyterian party argued, That the engagement of the Army ought to be no rule to the Councels of the Parliament; otherwiſe new Engagements every day may preſcribe the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment new Rules: we muſt look two wayes. 1. Upon the people unable to beare the burden. 2. Upon the Army. Let us keep ſome power in our owne Hands, and not deſcend ſo far below the dignity of a Parliament, as to put all into the hands of the Generall and his Councell of War. You have almoſt given away all already. The Army adviſeth you to keep up more Garriſons, then upon mature deliberation this Houſe formerly Voted: you have already many Garriſons manned with gallant and faithfull men, to whom you owe Arrears; to remove them, and place new Souldiers in their roomes, will neither pleaſe them, nor the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where they are quartered: who being acquainted with their old gueſts, will not willingly receive new in their roomes. Theſe men have done you as good and faithfull ſervice as any in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and were ready to obey you, and goe for <hi>Ireland,</hi> had they not been hindred by thoſe who under pretence of an engagement to the contrary (which they mutinouſly entred into) will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obey you, nor goe for <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor ſuffer others to goe. Though you diſcharge theſe men without paying their Arrears, (which others of other principles will not endure) yet give them good words: If you will be ſerved by none, but ſuch as are of your new principles; yet conſider your Army are not all alike principled, and peradventure the old principles may be as good as the new for publick, though not ſo fit for private deſignes and purpoſes. You have paſſed an Ordinance, <hi>That none that have borne Armes againſt the Parliament ſhall be imployed:</hi> if you disband all ſuch, your Army will be very thin; many have entred into pay there in order to doe the King ſervice, and bring the Parliament low. There is no reaſon you ſhould keep up 1400 Horſe more
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113968:24"/> then you laſt voted to keep up, being but 5800 at which time 60000l. a Month was thought an eſtabliſhment ſufficient both for <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> But now the whole charge of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> will amount to 114000l. a month: which muſt be raiſed upon the people, either directly and openly by way of ſeſſement; or indirectly and cloſely, partly by ſeſſements, and partly by free-quarter, and other devices: nor will the pay of 2<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. <hi>per diem</hi> to each Trouper, and 8<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. to each Foot Souldier enable them to pay their quarters. If you mean to govern by the Sword, your Army is too little: if by the Laws and Juſtice of the Land, and love of the people, your Army is too great: you can never pay them: which will occaſion mutinies in the Army, and ruine to the country. Thus diſputed the <hi>Preſbyterians,</hi> but to no purpoſe, it was carried againſt them.</p>
            <p>Obſerve that when the War was at the higheſt, the <hi>monthly tax</hi> came but to 54000l. yet had we then the Earle of <hi>Eſſex's</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Sir <hi>William Waller's,</hi> my Lord of <hi>Denbigh's,</hi> Maj. Gen: <hi>Poynt's,</hi> Maj. Gen: <hi>Maſſey's,</hi> Maj. Gen: <hi>Laughorne's,</hi> Sir <hi>William Bruerton's,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho: Middletons</hi> Brigades, and other Forces in the field, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Garriſons.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="56" place="margin">56. Monthly Taxes</note>But now this Army hath 60000l. a month, and 20000l. a month more <hi>pretended for Ireland;</hi> which running all through the fingers of the <hi>Committee of the Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="57" place="margin">57. <hi>Ireland</hi> why kept in a ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kept in a ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>That Kingdome (which is purpoſely kept in a <hi>ſtarving condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to break <hi>the Lord Inchequin's Army,</hi> that <hi>Ireland</hi> may be a <hi>receptacle for the Saints</hi> againſt <hi>England</hi> ſpewes them forth) hath nothing but the envy of it, the ſole benefit going to this Army: This 20000l. a month being a ſecret unknowne to the common Souldiers; The <hi>Grandees of the Army</hi> put it in their own purſes.</p>
            <p>Moreover, this Army hath ſtill a kind of free-quarter, (under colour of lodging, fire and candle) for who ſees not that theſe maſterleſſe gueſts upon that intereſt continued in our houſes, doe and will become Maſters of all the reſt? and who dares ask mony for quarter of them, or accept it when it is colourably offered, without feare of farther harme? beſides, the Army (whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts are now become commands) demanded that they might have the levying of this Tax: and that their accounts might be audited at the Head quarters: And though the Officers of this
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113968:24"/> Army (to catch the peoples affections) encouraged them often to petition the Houſes againſt Free-quarter, pretending they would forbear it, after an eſtabliſhment ſetled upon them; the uſe their party in the Houſe made of theſe Petitions was to move for an Addition of 20000l. or 30000l. a month) and then they ſhould pay their quarters, lodging, fire, and candle, nay ſtable-roome too excepted.</p>
            <p>Here it is not amiſſe to inſert a word or two of this villainous oppreſſion, <hi>Free-quarter;</hi>
               <note n="58" place="margin">58. Free-quarter.</note> whereby we are reduced to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of conquered Slaves, no man being maſter of his owne Family, but living like <hi>Bond-ſlaves</hi> in their own houſes, under theſe <hi>Aegyptian Task-masters,</hi> who are Spyes and Intelligencers upon our words and deeds, ſo that every mans table is become a ſnare to him. In the third year of King CHARLES, The Lords and Commons in their <hi>Petition of Right</hi> (when not above 2000 or 3000 Souldiers were thinly quartered upon the people but for a month or two) complained thereof to His Majeſty as a great Grievance contrary to the Laws and Cuſtomes of the Realme, and humbly prayed as their Right and Liberty, according to the Laws and Statutes of this Kingdom that he would remove them, and that his people might not be ſo burdened in time to come; which His Majeſty gratiouſly granted. Yet now we are ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more oppreſſed with them, and if theſe quarterers of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer violence or villainous uſage to any man in his houſe or family, or commit murder or felony, they are protected againſt the laws and juſtice of the land,<note n="59" place="margin">59. Martiall Law.</note> and <hi>Triable only by a Councell of War</hi> at the Head quarters, where a man can neither obtain juſtice, nor ſeek it with ſafety. So that we live under the burden of a perpetuall Army of 30000 or 40000 men, exempt from all but <hi>martiall law,</hi> which frequently oppreſſeth, ſeldome righteth any man: witneſſe <hi>Oliver Cromwell's</hi> taking of <hi>Thomſon</hi> (being no Souldier) from the Houſe of Commons dore with Souldiers, impriſoning and condemning him at a Councell of War, where he ſate Judge in his owne cauſe, there being a quarrell between them: Yet it was held Treaſon in the Earle of <hi>Strafford</hi> to condemn the Lord of <hi>Valentia</hi> ſo, being a member of his Army, becauſe it was in time of peace, as this was. Many other examples we have of the like nature, and of this Army, enough to perſwade us that theſe <hi>vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicative
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113968:25"/> Saints</hi> will not governe by the known <hi>Laws of the Land,</hi> (for which they have made us ſpend our money and bloud) but by <hi>Martiall Law</hi> and <hi>Committee Law,</hi> grounded upon Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ordinances of Parliament, which themſelves in the firſt part of <hi>exact Collections,</hi> pag. 727. confeſſe, are not Lawes without the Royall aſſent.</p>
            <p>This Army hath been daily recruited without any Authority, farre beyond the ſaid number or pay eſtabliſhed; the ſupernu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meraries living upon free quarter. And when complaints have been made thereof in the Houſe, the Army being quartered in ſeverall Brigades, <hi>ſupernumeraries</hi> have been <hi>disbanded in one Brigade,</hi> and their Armes <hi>taken by their Officers:</hi>
               <note n="60" place="margin">60. Cheats put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the State.</note> and ſhortly after they have been <hi>liſted againe in another Brigade,</hi> and their Armes <hi>ſold againe to the State,</hi> after a while to new Arme them. And of this ſort were thoſe Armes which being found in a Magazine in Town by ſome zelots, and rumoured to belong to the City for the Arming of Reformado's, were upon examination found to belong to <hi>Oliver Cromwell:</hi> ſo the buſineſſe was buried in ſilence: for though the Kings over-ſights muſt be <hi>tragically</hi> publiſhed to the world, yet the hainous crimes of <hi>the godly</hi> muſt lie hid under the <hi>maske of Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="61" place="margin">61. Arreares ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, although the State owes them nothing.</note>And though they have uſually taken <hi>free-quarter</hi> in one place, and taken <hi>compoſition money</hi> for free-quarter in another place, ſome of them in two or three places at once 3<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. a day, ſome of them 5<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. for a Trooper, and 1<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. a day, and 1<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. 6<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. for a foot Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, whereby no Arreares are due to them, but they owe money to the State; yet they have compelled the Houſes to ſettle upon them for <hi>pretended Arreares,</hi> 1. The moity of the Exciſe (that they may have the Souldiers help in leavying it. Although to flatter the People, the Army had formerly declared againſt the exciſe.) 2. The moity of <hi>Goldſmiths-Hall.</hi> 3. Remainder of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Lands. 4. The cuſtomes of ſome Garriſons. 5. Forreſt Lands.</p>
            <p>This Army brags they are <hi>the Saviours</hi> (nay Conquerors) of the Kingdome. Let them ſay when they ſaved it, whether at the fight at <hi>Nazeby,</hi> or taking in of <hi>Oxford:</hi> and we will pay them according to the then Liſt. And for all the Recruites taken in ſince the reducing of <hi>Oxford,</hi> it is fit they be disbanded without
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113968:25"/> pay, having been taken in without, nay againſt Authority, to drive on wicked deſignes, and enthrall <hi>King, Parliament, City,</hi> and <hi>Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1647.<note n="62" place="margin">62. Four dethro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Bills pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the King at <hi>Cariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brook-Caſtle.</hi>
               </note> The two Houſes by their Commiſſioners preſented to the King at <hi>Cariſbrook-Castle</hi> four Bills to be paſſed as Acts of Parliament, and divers Propoſitions to be aſſented to. They are all printed, ſo is His Majeſties Anſwer to them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall need to ſay the leſſe of them, only a word or two, to two of the Bills:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Act for raiſing, ſetling,</hi>
               <note n="63" place="margin">63. Act for the Militia.</note> 
               <hi>and maintaining Forces by Sea and Land, within the Kingdoms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, Wales, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (though it ſeems to be but for 20 years) deveſts the King, his Heirs, and Succeſſours of the power of the <hi>Militia</hi> for ever, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope of recovery but by repealing the ſaid Act, which will never be in his nor their power: for, firſt, it ſaith, <hi>That neither the King, nor his Heires or Succeſſours, nor any other ſhall exerciſe any power over the Militia by Land or Sea, but ſuch as ſhall act by authority and approbation of the ſaid Lords and Commons.</hi> That is, <hi>a Committee of State</hi> of twenty or thirty <hi>Grandees,</hi> to whom the two Houſes ſhall transfer this truſt, being over-awed by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, (for the ground-work of this Committee was layed by theſe words, though the Committee be erected ſince.) And ſecondly, it prohibiteth <hi>the King, his Heires and Succeſſours, &amp;c. after the expiration of the ſaid</hi> 20 <hi>years to exerciſe any of the ſaid powers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of the ſaid Lords and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons, and in all caſes wherein the ſaid Lords and Commons ſhall declare the ſafety of the Kingdome to be concerned after the ſaid</hi> 20 <hi>years expired, and ſhall paſſe any Bills for raiſing, arming, &amp;c. forces by land or ſea, or concerning levy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of mony, &amp;c. if the Royall aſſent to ſuch Bills ſhall not be given by ſuch a time, &amp;c. then ſuch Bills ſo paſſed by the Lords and Commons ſhall ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the force of Acts of Parliament without the Royall aſſent.</hi> Lo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re a foundation laid to make an <hi>Ordinance of both Houſes</hi> equall to an <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> if this be granted in one caſe, it will be taken in another, and then theſe Subverters of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Laws and Liberties will turne their uſurpation into a <hi>legall Tyranny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It gives an unlimited power to the two Houſes to raiſe what forces, and what numbers for land and ſea, and of what perſons
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113968:26"/> (without exceptions) they pleaſe, and to imploy them as they ſhall judge fit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To raiſe what mony they pleaſe for maintaining them, and in what ſort they think fit out of any mans eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="64" place="margin">64. Bill for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journment of the Parliament as well for place, as time.</note>The <hi>Bill for adjournment of both Houſes</hi> to any other <hi>place, &amp;c.</hi> will enable the engaged Party of the two Houſes and Army to adjourne the two Houſes <hi>from time to time,</hi> to or near the Head quarters of the Army: where thoſe Members that refuſe to enter into the ſame Engagement, ſhall neither ſit with accommodation nor ſafety, and ſo be ſhaken off at laſt: this is a new way of <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Houſes.</hi> Beſides, the Parliament following the motions of the Army, the King ſhall follow the Parliament, whereby the Army having both <hi>King and Parliament</hi> preſent with them, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever attempt ſhall be made againſt the Army ſhall be ſaid to be againſt the ſafety and authority of the <hi>King and Parliament,</hi> and a legall Treaſon, triable by Indictment, not a conſtructive Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon only Triable before the Lords.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="65" place="margin">65. The King's Anſwer deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>Monday 3. <hi>Jan.</hi> the <hi>Kings Anſwer</hi> to the ſaid Bills and Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions was <hi>debated in the Houſe of Commons.</hi> And firſt, Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Wrothe (Jacke Pudding</hi> to <hi>Prideaux</hi> the Poſt-maſter) had his cue to go high, and feel the pulſe of the Houſe; who ſpake to this purpoſe, That <hi>Bedlem</hi> was appointed for <hi>mad men,</hi> and <hi>Tophet</hi> for <hi>Kings:</hi> That our <hi>Kings</hi> of late had carried themſelves as if they were fit for no place but <hi>Bedlem:</hi> That his humble motion ſhould conſiſt of three parts:</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſecure the <hi>King,</hi> and keep Him cloſe in ſome inland Caſtle with ſure Guards.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To draw up Articles of Impeachment againſt Him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To lay Him by, and <hi>ſettle the Kingdome</hi> without Him. He cared not <hi>what form of Government</hi> they ſet up, ſo it were not <hi>by Kings and Devils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fretons</hi> Speech.</note>Then Commiſſary <hi>Ireton</hi> (ſeeming to ſpeak the ſenſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Army under the notion of many thouſand godly men who had ventured their lives to ſubdue their enemies) ſaid after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, The <hi>King</hi> had denied ſafety and protection to his people by denying their <hi>four Bills:</hi> That <hi>ſubjection to him</hi> was but in lieu of <hi>his protection to his people;</hi> This being denied they might well deny any more ſubjection to him, and ſettle the <hi>Kingdom</hi> without him:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113968:26"/> That it was now expected after ſo long patience they ſhould ſhew their reſolution, and not deſert thoſe valiant men who had engaged for them beyond all poſſibility of retreat, and would never forſake the Parliament, unleſſe the Parliament forſooke them firſt.</p>
            <p>After ſome more debate when the Houſe was ready for the queſtion, <hi>Cromwell</hi> brought up the Reare:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cromwell's</hi> Speech.</note> And giving an ample character of the valour, good affections, and godlineſſe of the Army, argued: That it was now expected the Parliament ſhould govern and defend the <hi>Kingdome</hi> by their own power and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and not teach the people any longer to expect ſafety and government from <hi>an obſtinate man</hi> whoſe heart God had hardned. That thoſe men who had defended the Parliament from ſo many dangers with the expence of their bloud, would defend them herein with fidelity and courage againſt all oppoſition. Teach them not by neglecting your owne and the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> ſafety (in which their owne is involved) to think themſelves betrayed: and left hereafter to the rage and malice of an irreconcilable enemy whom they have ſubdued for your ſake: and therefore are likely to find his future government of them inſupportable, and fuller of revenge then juſtice: leſt deſpair teach them to ſeek their ſafety by ſome other means then adhering to you, who will not ſtick to your ſelves. And how deſtructive ſuch a reſolution in them will be to you all, I tremble to think and leave you to judge.</p>
            <p>Obſerve, he laid his hand upon his Sword at the latter end of his Speech; that Sword which being by his ſide could not keep him from trembling when Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton</hi> baffled him in the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>This concluding Speech having ſomething of menace in it was thought very prevalent with the Houſe.<note n="66" place="margin">66. The four Bills for no addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes nor applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions paſſed.</note> The firſt of the foure Queſtions being put, <hi>That the two Houſes ſhould make no more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes nor applications to the King:</hi> The Houſe of Commons was divided, 141. <hi>yeas,</hi> 91. <hi>noes,</hi> ſo it was carried in the affirmative. The other three Votes followed theſe votes with facility: ſee them in print.<note n="67" place="margin">67. The Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fety revived and enlarged.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Members had been locked into the Houſe of Commons from before nine of the clock in the morning to ſeven at night, and then the dores were unlocked, and what Members would, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113968:27"/> to go forth, whereby many <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> thinking the Houſe had been upon riſing departed; when preſently (the Houſe being grown thin) the Vote to revive the Committee of both Kingdoms called <hi>the Committee of Safety at Darby Houſe,</hi> paſſed by Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance dated 3. <hi>Janu.</hi> 1647. in theſe words: <hi>Reſolved, &amp;c. That the powers formerly granted by both Houſes to the Committee of both Kingdomes,</hi> (viz. England and Scotland) <hi>in relation to the two Kingdomes of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>be now granted and veſted in the Members of both Houſes only that are of that Committee, with power to them alone, to put the ſame in execution.</hi> The originall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance that firſt erected this Committee, and to which this ſaid Ordinance relates, beareth date 7. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1643. in which the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Committees were appointed from time to time, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound to the <hi>Scottiſh Commiſſioners</hi> whatſoever they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in charge from both Houſes, and to make report to both Houſes, to direct the managing of the War, and to keep good correſpondency with forain States, and to receive directions from time to time from both Houſes; and to continue for three moneths and no longer.<note place="margin">The Members of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee are now: The Earl of <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. Ro.</hi> Earl of <hi>Warwick.</hi> The E. of <hi>Kent. Edw:</hi> Earl of <hi>Mancheſter. Will.</hi> Lord <hi>Say</hi> &amp; <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Phil.</hi> L. <hi>Wharton. John</hi> Lord <hi>Roberts. Will. Pierre. poynt.</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> ſen. Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerrarde.</hi> Sir <hi>Will. Armine.</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Haſterig.</hi> Sir <hi>Hen. Vanc,</hi> Iun. <hi>John Crew. Rob. Wallope. Oliver</hi> St. <hi>Johns</hi> Sol. <hi>Oliver Cromwell. Samu. Browne. Nath. Fiennes.</hi> Sir <hi>John Eveline,</hi> Iunior.</note> But this Ordinance 3 <hi>Janu.</hi> 1647. veſts the ſaid powers in <hi>the Members thereof only,</hi> and alone: words exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the two Houſes: and for <hi>a time indefinite.</hi> There were then added to this Committee, <hi>Nathaniel Fiennes,</hi> in place of Sir <hi>Phil. Stapleton;</hi> Sir <hi>John Evelin Junior,</hi> in place of Mr. Recorder; and the Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> in ſtead of the Earl of <hi>Eſſex.</hi> 22. <hi>Janu.</hi> following, the Lords ſent down a Meſſage for a farther power to this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee; which was granted in theſe words: <hi>Power to ſuppreſſe Tumults and Inſurrections in England, &amp;c. and at</hi> Barwick, <hi>and for that purpoſe the Committee to have power to give orders and directions to all the Militia and forces of the Kingdome.</hi> The addition of four Lords and eight Commoners likewiſe to this Committee was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but denyed.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="68" place="margin">68. <hi>White-Hall</hi> and the <hi>Mewes</hi> Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſoned.</note>Friday 14 <hi>Janu.</hi> after a long debate it was ordered that Sir <hi>Lewis Dives,</hi> Sir <hi>John Stowell,</hi> and <hi>David Jenkins,</hi> be tryed as Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors at the Kings Bench: the Grand Jury had found the Bill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Jenkins.</hi> Maſter Solicitor, &amp;c. appointed to manage the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113968:27"/> buſineſſe, * but <hi>Jenkins</hi> is ſo great a Lawyer,<note place="margin">See Iudge <hi>Jen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance to the Lords and Commons of Par. 21. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1647.</note> that the Solicitor durſt not venture upon him, the long ſword being more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in his mouth then the Law; wherefore the Solicitor found an <hi>Errour in the Indictment,</hi> turned him back againe upon the Houſe to be impeached before the Lords, to whoſe Juriſdiction he pleaded: ſo the Solicitor put the affront from himſelf upon the Houſes. It was now 12. of the clock, and many of the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> party began to cry, Riſe, riſe; The Presbyterians thinking all had been done: many went to dinner, yet the <hi>Independents</hi> ſate ſtill: and finding the Houſe for their turne, moved, That a Letter might be forthwith ſent to Sir <hi>Tho: Fairfax,</hi> to ſend a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent number <hi>to Garriſon White-Hall;</hi> and a party of Horſe <hi>to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Mewes.</hi> The Lords concurrence was not deſired to this Vote, but the Letters immediately drawn and ſent.</p>
            <p>Obſerve that before this Vote paſſed, diverſe forces were upon their March towards the Towne, and came to <hi>White-Hall</hi> Saterday following by eight of the Clock in the morning.</p>
            <p>Saterday, 15. <hi>Janu.</hi>
               <note n="69" place="margin">69. The Armies Declaration thanking the Commons for their 4 Votes.</note> The Army ſent a Declaration to the Houſe of Commons, Thanking them for their 4 <hi>Votes</hi> againſt the King, and promiſing <hi>to live and die with the Commons,</hi> in defence of them againſt all opponents. Many of the <hi>Lords</hi> had argued very hotly againſt the ſaid 4 Votes, inſomuch that it was ten Lords to ten; but this engagement of the Army,<note n="70" place="margin">70. The Lords paſſe the 4 Votes</note> and the unexpected garriſoning of <hi>White-Hall</hi> and <hi>the Mewes,</hi> turned the ſcales: ſo that <hi>they paſſed</hi> the ſaid 4 <hi>Votes,</hi> only adding a ſhort preamble (little to the purpoſe) holding forth ſome reaſons for paſſing them, to which the Commons, when they came down, aſſented. When preſently (about 12. of the clock the Houſe being thin) <hi>Dennis Bond</hi> moved, That whoſoever ſhould act againſt thoſe 4 Votes, or incite others to act againſt them, ſhould be impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſequeſtred.</p>
            <p>Three or four dayes after the <hi>Lords</hi> had paſſed the ſaid 4 <hi>Votes,</hi>
               <note n="71" place="margin">71. The Army thanks the Lords.</note> the <hi>Army</hi> vouchſafed to <hi>ſpit thanks in their mouthes,</hi> and make much of them. Theſe 4 Votes were generally ſiniſterly taken, and filled mens mindes with ſuſpicion, what forme of government the <hi>Grandees</hi> would ſet up, now they had laid by the <hi>King:</hi> and every mans minde preſaged a new War; which they conceived the <hi>Independent Grandees</hi> were willing to have, to colour their
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113968:28"/> keeping up this Army, and raiſing money to maintaine them: and every man began to lay the project of a new War at their door: notwithſtanding (by way of prevention) they had <hi>impeached divers Members and Citizens of London,</hi> for endeavouring a new Warre when they did but raiſe men for their ſelfe-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="72" place="margin">72. The Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the King.</note>To ſhew the people therefore, the reaſons of theſe 4 <hi>Votes,</hi> the <hi>Independent Grandees</hi> appointed a Committee to ſearch into the <hi>Kings</hi> Converſation, &amp; errours of his Government, &amp; publiſh them in a <hi>Declaration</hi> to the world: wherein they objected many high crimes againſt Him, concerning His Fathers death, the loſſe of <hi>Rochell,</hi> and the <hi>Maſſacre</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> in <hi>Ireland:</hi> which upon debate in the Houſe, were very much moderated by the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians:</hi> of which <hi>Declaration</hi> I will only ſay, That they have ſet forth no new matter therein, which they have not formerly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in parcells: ſince which time they have taken and cauſed others to take the Nationall Covenant; whereby they vow to maintaine the Kings Perſon, Crown and Dignity, in defence of Religion, Laws, and Liberties: and therefore to reprint only the ſame things as Arguments to lay by the <hi>King,</hi> ſavours more of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, then juſtice. I will wade no farther in the cenſure of the ſaid Declaration, leſt I imitate the Authors of it: and as they by a feeble accuſation have done the <hi>King</hi> much right, ſo I by a weak defence ſhould doe him much wrong. The people were as ill ſatisfied with this Declaration as with the four Votes,<note n="73" place="margin">73. <hi>Tho: Haſterig's</hi> Letter concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the King.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 24. <hi>Febr.</hi> Mr. Speaker, with much ſeriouſneſſe, preſented to the Houſe a Letter out of <hi>Leiceſter-ſhire</hi> from <hi>Thomas Haſterig,</hi> (brother to Sir <hi>Arthur</hi>) which was read to this purpoſe, That there was one Mr. <hi>Smalling</hi> a Committee-man of <hi>Leiceſter-ſhire,</hi> who had been a Deputy-examiner in the <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that above twenty years ſince there being a ſuite in <hi>Star-chamber</hi> betweene the Earle of <hi>Briſtoll</hi> complainant, and the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> defendant, concerning Phyſick preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly adminiſtred by the ſaid Duke to <hi>K. James,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Smalling</hi> took many depoſitions therein, and was farther proceeding in the Examinations, untill a Warrant ſigned by the <hi>King</hi> was brought him, commanding him to ſurceaſe and to ſend him the Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions already taken; which <hi>Smalling</hi> did: yet kept notes by him
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113968:28"/> of the principall paſſages, doubting what farther proceedings might be hereafter, in a buſineſſe of ſuch importance. Sir <hi>Henry Mildmay</hi> moved that <hi>Smalling</hi> be ſent for and examined upon oath by the Committee that penned the ſaid Declaration: but upon motion of the Presbyterians, he was ordered to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the Commons Bar. <hi>Smalling</hi> came, produced the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, but no notes: ſo this <hi>Chimaera</hi> vaniſhed. What the ſaid Committee would have made of this, who knows? God bleſſe us all from clandeſtine examinations, eſpecially when they are taken by parties preingaged. 3. <hi>Caroli</hi> this buſineſſe had been ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilated and examined againſt the Duke, and no mention made of poyſoning or killing K. <hi>James,</hi> It was then only called <hi>an Act of high preſumption and dangerous conſequence in the Duke:</hi> nor was there then the leaſt reflection upon <hi>K. Charls;</hi> yet now becauſe <hi>K. Charls</hi> diſſolved that Parliament, the Independent party were willing to raiſe a ſuſpition againſt him concerning his Fathers death: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Accuſation againſt the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> 3 <hi>Caroli</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſeven or eight Charges againſt him, the leaſt whereof might occaſion the diſſolving of that Parliament.</p>
            <p>Theſe deſperate courſes (to diſhonour the <hi>King</hi> and make him uncapable of Government, to ruine his Perſon, Crown,<note n="74" place="margin">74. Why the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents went ſo high againſt the King: To uſurp the Regall power into themſelves either in the Houſes pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging: or in the Committee of ſafety at <hi>Derby houſe.</hi>
               </note> and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and extirpate Monarchy root and branch) were taken in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the <hi>uſurping of the Kingly power into the Grandees of the Parliament and Army,</hi> and in caſe they could not purge the two Houſes and make them wholly Independent, (which they now diſpair of) then into the hands of <hi>the Committee,</hi> or Councell of State at <hi>Derby Houſe,</hi> and <hi>Grandees of the Army.</hi> In order to which, they are now contriving to ſtrengthen the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee with more power and more Members, and to adjourn the Parliament and ſend downe the Presbyterian Members into the Country upon pretence of ſervice, where if any Tumults happen (for which their extortions will give ſufficient provocation) the ſaid diſſenting Members ſhall bear the blame; and have Blanck Impeachments given them to purge them out of the Houſes, if not out of the world; or at leaſt be ſequeſtred: for now they have ſqueezed what they can out of the <hi>Kings</hi> party by Sequeſtrations, the next fuell to their covetouſneſſe is to ſequeſter the <hi>Preſbyeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> and then to ſequeſter one another: for they are already di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113968:29"/> into <hi>pure Independents</hi> and <hi>mixed Independents,</hi> and have feuds amongſt themſelves, for this Faction; (inſatiate with mony and bloud) are all beaſts of prey, and when they want prey, will prey upon one another: nor ſhall the Houſes meet above one Month or two in a Year to ratifie and approve what <hi>Derby houſe</hi> and the <hi>Junto</hi> of the Army ſhall dictate to them: and to give an Account to the domineering party how each Member hath car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried himſelf in the Country: Thus in ſtead of <hi>one King,</hi> we ſhall have <hi>twenty</hi> or <hi>thirty Tyrants</hi> in chief, and as many ſubordinate Tyrants as they pleaſe to imploy under them, with the Iron yoak of an Army to hold us in ſubjection to their Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="75" place="margin">75. Why the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees doe ſtill continue to truck with the King: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſaid 4 Votes.</note>Notwithſtanding the aforeſaid four Votes and Reſolutions, the Caball of <hi>Grandees</hi> ſtill keep <hi>Aſhburnham</hi> and <hi>Barkley</hi> in the Army, and have ſent diverſe <hi>turn-coat-Cavaleers, and Emiſſaries</hi> underhand <hi>diſguiſed to the King,</hi> who pretending that by Bribes they have bought their admiſſion to him, after ſome inſinuations endevour with falſe and deceitfull newes and arguments to ſhake his conſtancy: and perſwade him <hi>to paſſe</hi> the ſaid 4. <hi>dethroning Bils;</hi> (for theſe uſurpers of Soveraign Authority long to turne their Armed and violent Tyrannie into a legall Tyrannie) or (at leaſt) to make him <hi>declare againſt the Scots comming in.</hi> In both which caſes he will diſhearten his friends, who endeavour to take the golden reines of Government out of the gripes of theſe <hi>Phaëtons,</hi> and reſtore them againe to his hand, un-king himſelf and his poſterity for ever, be carryed up and down like a ſtalking horſe to their deſignes, and be Crowned <hi>Ludibrio Coronae,</hi> with ſtraw or thornes. For who can think that at the end of 20 yeares, theſe Uſurpers will lay down what they have ſo unjuſtly contrary to all Laws, Divine and Humane, and contrary to their owne <hi>Declarations, Oaths</hi> and <hi>Covenants</hi> extorted? and who can or dare wreſt thoſe powers out of their hands, being once ſetled and grown cuſtomary in them: the peoples ſpirits broken with an habituall ſervitude; a numerous Army and Garriſons hove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring over them; and all places of Judicature filled with corrupt Judges; who ſhall by conſtrained interpretations of the Law, force bloudy preſidents out of them, againſt whoſoever ſhall dare to be ſo good a Patriot as to oppoſe their Tyrannie? They
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:113968:29"/> that could make ſteel ſharp enough to cut Captain <hi>Barlyes</hi> throat for attempting to reſcue the King out of the hands of a <hi>rebellious Army</hi> that neither <hi>obeyes King nor Parliament,</hi> will find <hi>gold</hi> and <hi>ſilver</hi> enough to <hi>corrupt all the Judges,</hi> they mean to prefer and make them <hi>wyld</hi> and <hi>vilde</hi> enough for their purpoſes. But it is hoped he hath more of King, more of man in him then to loſe his principles, and ſtumble againe at the ſame ſtone, daſh againe upon the ſame rock, whatſoever Syrens ſing upon it; knowing he hath a Son at liberty to revenge his wrongs, all the Princes of Chriſtendome his Allyes, whoſe common cauſe is controverted in his ſufferings, the greateſt men of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> of his bloud, and the people generally (whoſe fartheſt deſigne was to preſerve their Lawes and Liberties, and to defend the Parliament from being conquered by the Sword) looking with an angry aſpect upon theſe Seducers, who by inſenſible degrees and many forgeries have engaged them farther then they intended, not to the <hi>defence of Religion, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> but to the <hi>ſetting up of Schiſme, Committee law, and Martiall law, Impeachments before the Lords, and unlimited ſlavery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I am confident this Faction deſpaire of working upon the <hi>King,</hi> who like a rock <hi>in mediis tutiſſimus undis,</hi> whatſoever reports they give out to the contrary, having from the beginning made <hi>lies</hi> their refuge, which being wiſely foreſeen by the <hi>King,</hi> he ſent a <hi>Meſſage</hi> to both Houſes, (by way of prevention) delivered in the <hi>painted Chamber</hi> by the Lord of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> one of the Scots Commiſſioners: conſiſting of three heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That He was taken from</hi> Holdenby <hi>againſt His will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That they ſhould maintain the Honour and Priviledges of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That they ſhould believe no Meſſage as coming from Him du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring His Reſtraint in the Army, but ſhould only credit what they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from His own mouth.</hi> Theſe Grandees have cheated all the intereſts of the Kingdom, and have lately attempted the City a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and had the repulſe. But the <hi>King</hi> is their old cuſtomer, and hath been often cheated by them, and having Him in ſtrict cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, peradventure they may perſwade Him it is for His Safety to be deceived once more: wherefore (notwithſtanding their many endeavours to root up Monarchy, dethrone the King, and his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:113968:30"/> and uſurp His power: in order to which, they have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed Him, and all His, with innumerable calamities and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches) yet ſince the paſſing of the Declaration againſt the King, their deſperate condition hath enforced them to make new addreſſes in private to Him: notwithſtanding their four Votes inflicting the penalty of Treaſon upon the infringers. But Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is as naturall to <hi>Cromwell</hi> as <hi>falſe-accuſing, proteſting</hi> and <hi>ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> he is ſo ſuperlative a Traytor, that the Laws can lay no hold of him. Lieut. Col. <hi>Lylborne,</hi> in a verball Charge delivered at the Commons Bar, accuſed him of many Treaſonable acts, which the avoweth to make good: and in his Book, called, <hi>A Plea for a Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas Corpus:</hi> But as if <hi>Cromwell</hi> were a Traytor <hi>cum privilegio,</hi> the Houſe of Commons (being under his armed Guards) dares take no notice of it. But the Roman Tribune ſaid to <hi>Scipio Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus,</hi> in <hi>Livy, Qui jus aequum ferre non poteſt, in eum vim hand injuſtam fore,</hi> He that exalts himſelf above the law, ought not to be protected by the law.</p>
            <p>To conclude, <hi>Cromwell</hi> hath lately had private conference at <hi>Farnham</hi> with <hi>Hammond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Earle of <hi>Southampton</hi> hath been courted to negotiate with the King, and offered the two Speakers hands for his warrant.</p>
            <p>Capt. <hi>Titus</hi> taken into favour, and imployed that way.</p>
            <p>Theſe Grandees have brought themſelves into a miſt, and now wander from one fooliſh deſigne to another.</p>
            <p>The Spaniard is ſaid to forecaſt in his debates, what will happen forty years after. But theſe purblind Politicians doe not foreſee the event of their Councels forty daies, nay howers beforehand; but it is a curſe laid upon wicked men, to grope at noone day.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="76" place="margin">76. Debates in the Houſe of Commons up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Scots Letters.</note>
               <note n="1" place="margin">1. Concerning the ſaid four Votes.</note>About the 5. or 6. of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1647. the Scots Commiſſioners had written certaine Letters to the Houſe of Commons; one whereof <hi>repeating the four Votes against the King;</hi> propounded to know, <hi>whether the Houſes by their Votes, That no perſon whatſoever do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to make or receive any Application or addreſſe to, or from the King; would debar the Scots to make or receive any Addreſſes to or from him, and ſo put an incapacity upon Him to perform Acts of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment towards them.</hi> In the debate, the <hi>Independents</hi> called to mind a more antient Vote, whereby it was ordered, <hi>That the Scots might be admitted to the King.</hi> Againſt which, was alleaged. <hi>That
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:113968:30"/> theſe latter Votes being made generall, without exception, Repealed that former Vote.</hi> At laſt by an interpretative Vote, it was conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>That notwithstanding the ſaid four latter Votes:</hi> the former Vote, <hi>That the Scots Commiſſioners might make Addreſſes to the King,</hi> was ſtill in force. Obſerve that this was done four or five daies after the Scots Commiſſioners were on their way towards <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Letter was concerning 100000l. <hi>due by contract to the Scots from the Parliament,</hi>
               <note n="2" place="margin">2. Concerning 100000l. due to the Scots.</note> 
               <hi>whereof</hi> 50000l. <hi>was payable by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignement to divers Scots Gentlemen who had advanced money to haſten the Scots Army to our Relief; whereof</hi> 10000l. <hi>was payable to the Earle of Argyle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Henry Mildmay</hi> made a long Speech in praiſe of <hi>Argyle,</hi> ſaying, <hi>That he and his party, and the Scottiſh Clergy were the onely men that upheld the Engliſh interest in</hi> Scotland, <hi>and were better friends to us then all</hi> Scotland <hi>beſides:</hi> wherefore he moved <hi>that Argyle might be payed his</hi> 10000l. <hi>and the reſt continued at Intereſt at</hi> 81. <hi>per cent.</hi> Preſently the whole Independent gang, with much zeale and little diſcretion, ran that way, untill more moderate men ſtopping them in full cry, minded them what diſhonour and danger they might bring their friends into by laying him open to ſuſpition.</p>
            <p>After this, it was Reſolved to ſend <hi>four Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons,</hi>
               <note n="77" place="margin">77. Six Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>two Lords</hi> into <hi>Scotland</hi> as <hi>Commiſſioners,</hi> with Inſtructions: to ſend all Independents, would not be acceptable; Two Presbyterians Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners therefore were ſent, one whereof was ſweetned with the guift of 1000l. and an Office before they would truſt him: with them were ſent Mr. <hi>Hearle</hi> and Mr. <hi>Marſhall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marſhall,</hi> when he ſaw Independency prevaile,<note n="78" place="margin">78. M. <hi>Marſhall.</hi>
               </note> had ſecretly <hi>turned his coat</hi> the wrong ſide outward, and joyned intereſt with Mr. <hi>Nye.</hi> But before he declared himſelf, he was to do ſome ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for his new party: Wherefore when the Army looked with a threatning poſture upon the Parliament and City, before they marched through <hi>London,</hi> (the common Souldiers being in ſuch diſcontent for want of pay that they were ready to mutiny and disband, and their Officers ſcarce daring to governe them) the firſt fruits of <hi>Marſhall's</hi> ſervice to his new friends was to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the City to lend the Parliament 50000l. to pacifie the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:113968:31"/> Souldiers: aſſuring them by Letters that <hi>the Army had nothing but good thoughts towards the City, onely the common Souldiers was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for want of pay:</hi> after the City had laid down the ſaid 50000l. his next labour was, to perſwade the Citizens to <hi>let the Army march through the City without oppoſition for avoiding of bloudſhed and firing: and to let them poſſeſſe the Tower, and Line of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</hi> After theſe ſervices, the <hi>Grandees</hi> of the Parliament and Army, finding him ſutable to them, received him into an avowed favour; and then four <hi>Independents,</hi> and four <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines (conjoyning their intereſts) were ſent to ſeaſon the Army, and new tune them according to the more moderne deſigne: <hi>Marſhall</hi> was one; where, after he had preached according to the Dictates of the Grandees of the two Houſes and Army for divers weeks, <hi>Marſhall</hi> was thought fit to attend the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners into <hi>Scotland:</hi> He and Mr. <hi>Nye</hi> had been ſent to <hi>Carisbrooke</hi> Caſtle formerly with thoſe Commiſſioners that carried the four Bills to the King, and had 500l. a piece given them for their journey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scotland,</hi> a longer journey, promiſed a larger reward: it is good being a poſtilion of the Goſpel at ſuch rates.</p>
            <p>The Sunday before he went, he preached at <hi>Margarets Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> and as much cried up Presbytery and the Covenant there, as he had before ſlighted them in the Army. This was a <hi>prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Sermon</hi> to make him acceptable to the Scots, that he might cajole them the eaſier. Before he went he ſent his Agents from houſe to houſe at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to beg mens good wills towards his journey. He was willing upon this pretence to get what he could from St. <hi>Margarets</hi> Pariſh, where he found the people to grow cold in their affections and contributions to him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having made his bargain before he went, to leave S. <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets,</hi> and officiate in the <hi>Abby,</hi> where he is to have 300l. <hi>per annum</hi> certain allowance, he would rob the Aegyptians at S. <hi>Margarets</hi> for a parting blow. This Prieſt married his owne Daughter with the Book of <hi>Common-prayer</hi> and a <hi>Ring,</hi> and gave for reaſon, <hi>That the Statute eſtabliſhing that Liturgy was not yet repealed, and he was loath to have his Daughter whored, and turned back upon him for want of a Legall Mariage:</hi> yet he can declare againſt all uſe of it by others. He hath ſo long curſed <hi>Meroz</hi> and <hi>neutrality,</hi> that he
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:113968:31"/> hath brought Gods curſe upon the land: and hath put Church and Common-wealth into <hi>a flame,</hi> but himſelf and his Brats have <hi>warmed their fingers</hi> at it: as monies are decried or enhaunced by the Kings authority, ſo is every mans Religion cried up or down by <hi>Marſhall's</hi> authority and ſtamp.</p>
            <p>About the 24.<note n="79" place="margin">79. The Anſwer to the Scots De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration.</note> 
               <hi>Feb.</hi> the <hi>Anſwer to the Scots Declaration</hi> began to be debated in parts: in which Debate the <hi>Covenant</hi> was much undervalued, and called <hi>an Almanack out of Date. Nath: Fiennes</hi> argued againſt it, That that clauſe in the Covenant, <hi>[To defend the Kings Perſon, Crown, and Dignity, &amp;c.]</hi> was inconſiſtent with their four Votes, <hi>for making no Addreſſes to the King:</hi> To which was anſwered by ſome, <hi>That then they would relinquiſh the foure Votes and adhere to the Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the beginning of <hi>March,</hi>
               <note n="80" place="margin">80. Mony ſhared amongſt godly Members.</note> was given to Col. <hi>Sydenham</hi> and Col. <hi>Bingham</hi> 1000l. apiece, as part of their Arrears: their Accounts not yet ſtated. To the Lord of <hi>Broghill</hi> 2000l. To Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Fenwicke</hi> 500l. for loſſes. To Mr. <hi>Millington</hi> 2000l. for loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. To Col. <hi>Ven</hi> 4000l. notwithſtanding it was moved he might firſt account for Contribution-money, the Plunder of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try about <hi>Windſor,</hi> and the Kings Houſhold-ſtuffe, Hangings, Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, and Bedding. Mr. <hi>Pury</hi> the Petty-bag Office, beſides 1000l. formerly given him. To <hi>Pury's</hi> Son, the Clerke of the Peers place, and 100l. a yeare: all <hi>Independents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 7. of <hi>March,</hi>
               <note n="81" place="margin">81. <hi>Cromwell.</hi>
               </note> an Ordinance paſſed the Commons to ſettle 2500l. a year land, out of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Worceſter's</hi> Eſtate, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Lieutenant Generall <hi>Oliver Cromwell.</hi> I have heard ſome Gentlemen, that know the Mannor of <hi>Chepstow,</hi> and the reſt of the Lands ſetled upon him, affirm, That in the particulars the ſaid Lands are ſo favourably rated, that they are worth 5000l. or 6000l. a year: It is farther ſaid thoſe Lands are bravely wooded. You ſee though they have not made King <hi>Charles, a glorious King,</hi>
               <note n="82" place="margin">82. A Meſſage from the Lords, deſiring the Commons concurrence to the engagement of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers with the Army.</note> as they promiſed: yet they have ſetled a <hi>crowne Revenue</hi> upon <hi>Oliver,</hi> and have made him as great and glorious a <hi>king</hi> as ever <hi>John of Leyden</hi> was. Wonder not that they conſpire to keep up this Army, as well to make good theſe Largeſſes, as to keep their guilty Heads upon their ſhoulders.</p>
            <p>Thurſday, 9. <hi>March,</hi> the Lords ſent a Meſſage to the Houſe of Commons, <hi>To deſire their concurrence to the Engagement of thoſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:113968:32"/> Members that fled to the Army,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment approved by Threats.</note> 
               <hi>to live and die with the Army.</hi> It was Debated all day, untill ſeven of the clock at night; and at laſt the queſtion put, <hi>That this Houſe doth approve the ſubſcription of the ſaid Members to the ſaid Ingagement.</hi> The Houſe divided upon the queſtion, <hi>yeas</hi> 100. <hi>noes</hi> 91. Obſerve 1. that Mr. Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>Haſterig,</hi> and many more, when they perceived difficulty in paſſing it, began to skirmiſh with their long ſword againe. And many told them, <hi>they muſt give content without dores</hi> (meaning, to the Army) <hi>as well at within, or elſe all would go naught.</hi> 2. 44 Of thoſe Members that engaged with the Army ſate in the Houſe, and voted in their owne caſe; many of them carrying themſelves very high and inſolently in their geſtures and expreſſions. 3. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Presbyterians left the Houſe becauſe it was late, and ſome (as it is thought) not daring to vote in the negative. 4. This en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement about ſix Months agoe had been ſent to the Commons by the Lords once or twice, and was rejected; yet now was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded upon them again by the Lords, who would not acquieſce; contrary to the Priviledges of the Houſe of Commons. 5. This approbation thus ſurreptitiouſly gotten, is equall to a Pardon ſued forth before conviction, which in law amounteth to a confeſſion of the crime.<note n="83" place="margin">83. The temper of the Houſe tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, had the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement not been approved, a new Charge from the Army intended.</note> 6. The <hi>Agitators</hi> tell you in <hi>Derby-houſe projects,</hi> p. 7. <hi>That this engagement was ſent down to the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons to try the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per of the Houſe, and if the Houſe had not approved of the Engagement, the reſolution of their ſecret Councel was to flie to their Arms, and make a new Charge againſt their principall Oppoſers;</hi> for they acknowledge amongſt themſelves, <hi>that they Rule by power only, and that the Houſe of Commons is no longer theirs then they over-awe them, and that they fear the Criticall day will come which will diſcover the Parliament to be no longer theirs then while they have a force upon it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As men ready to ſinke, embrace every ſhadow of help, and catch hold of leaves, twigs, and bulruſhes, to ſupport them: ſo theſe deſperate and purblind Projectors, having engaged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a way of Tyranny, out of which, they can find no iſſue; lay hold of frivolous inventions to peer up from time to time their ill laid deſignes, like the man in the parable <hi>that patched up his old Garment with new cloth,</hi>
               <note n="84" place="margin">84. A project to unite all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts.</note> 
               <hi>which breaking out again left the rent wider then it was before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their laſt project was <hi>to unite all intereſts in the Houſes, City
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:113968:32"/> and Army:</hi> To which purpoſe <hi>Cromwell</hi> (the heavieſt, baſeſt and moſt ridiculous Tyrant that ever our noble Nation groaned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) made a Speech in the Houſe of Commons: to which was anſwered, <hi>That the Members were choſen and truſted by the people to purſue on common intereſt,</hi> which was, <hi>the common good, the Safety and Liberty of the people: and whoſoever had any peculiar intereſt eccentricke from that, was not fit to ſit in that Aſſembly, and deſerved to be called to a ſtrict account by thoſe that truſted him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerve that the extent of this project was to conjoyne theſe <hi>three intereſts</hi> for upholding the greatneſſe of the Grandees, in the <hi>Parliament, City,</hi> and <hi>Army;</hi> for in all three the vulgar mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and the more modeſt and honeſt ſort, are but in the ſame condition with other men: The Parliament bearing the <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> the Army the <hi>Sword,</hi> and the City the <hi>Purſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> ſhall be the Task-maſters, and impoſe Tribute.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond,</hi> the Sheriffs, or rather Free-booters, and leavy it by diſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>third,</hi> the Brokers to receive it, and buy it off.</p>
            <p>But it pleaſed God to beſtow ſo much providence and integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon the City, that when upon Saterday, 8. <hi>April,</hi> 1648. <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> and his fellow Grandees offered this temptation (at a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Councell) to them;</p>
            <p>The City grew wiſer then our firſt Parents, and rejected the Serpent and his ſubtilties, in ſo much that <hi>Cromwell</hi> netled with the affront, called his Solicitor <hi>Glover</hi> to account by what autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity he had offered the <hi>reſtitution of their Tower and Militia, and the enlargment of their accuſed Aldermen:</hi> who anſwered, <hi>he did it by his authority</hi> &amp; delivered him a Warrant to that purpoſe ſigned by Sir <hi>Tho: Fairfax. Oliver Cromwell,</hi> Mr. Solicitor, and young Sir <hi>Henry Vane:</hi> which <hi>Cromwell</hi> had the impudence to put in his pocket.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cromwell</hi> had felt the pulſe of the City long before by his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents <hi>Glover</hi> and <hi>Watkins,</hi>
               <note n="85" place="margin">85. A device to put the Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into a Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult.</note> and found them averſe from comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him: wherefore (being a man of an early as well as an implacable malice) he (by advice of the Committee of <hi>Derby-houſe</hi>) caſt about with the ſchiſmaticall Lord Mayor <hi>Warne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> (he that raiſed the ridiculous Tumult at Chriſtmas about Roſemary and Bayes: a man that had been choſen Mayor by power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:113968:33"/> (out of courſe) to carry on the deſigne of the Faction) and with the Lieutenant of the Tower how to put the City into ſome diſtemper, of which they might take advantage. The Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens were well acquainted with their jugling tricks, they had no hopes to work upon them: wherefore they contrived how to put a provocation upon the ſilly Apprentice Boyes, and put them forth into ſome raſh action, of which they might make uſe to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on their deſignes againſt the whole City: wherefore upon Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-day, 1647. in the evening ſome few Apprentices playing in <hi>Finniſbury fields,</hi> ſome Souldiers were ſent to drive them away; which they did, and impriſoned ſome of them for not readily o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying: Upon Sunday following, 9. <hi>April,</hi> divers Apprentices be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at play (according to cuſtome) in <hi>Moore fields,</hi> the Mayor ſent Captaine <hi>Gale</hi> (one of the new Captains of the Hamlets, a Silke-Throſter and a Tub-preacher, and one that ran away at the Fight at <hi>Newbury-waſh,</hi> and hid himſelf in a Ditch, as my L. <hi>Wharton</hi> at the Battle of <hi>Keynton</hi> hid himſelf in a Saw-pit) thither to diſturbe them, with about 50. or 60. of his Trained Band and no more (that he might the better encourage the Boyes to reſiſt him) who ſurlily asking them <hi>what they did there;</hi> ſome of them anſwered, <hi>they did no harm but only play, and ſince all Holydaies have been Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted down they had no other time of recreation:</hi> The Captain inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently commanded them to <hi>be gone:</hi> they replied, <hi>he had no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſo to doe,</hi> and continued playing: whereupon the Captaine commanded his Muſquetiers to <hi>ſhoot amongst them;</hi> which they forbearing, he took a Muſquet himſelf, and diſcharged amongſt them, when preſently two or three ſchiſmaticall Muſquetiers of his Company following his example diſcharged upon them like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and killed (or as the Schiſmaticks ſay, wounded onely) one of the Boyes: whereat the Boyes making a great out-cry, more company gathered to them, and ſo with ſtones, Brick-bats, and ſticks they diſperſed the Trained Bands: and at laſt, got their Colours, and inſtantly in a childiſh jollity marched (unarmed as they were) towards the <hi>Mewes,</hi> when preſently a party of Horſe (ready prepared for this fore-laid deſigne) met them, charged and with eaſe routed them, <hi>Cromwell</hi> himſelfe animating the Troupers <hi>to ſhoot and ſpit them, and to ſpare neither man, woman, nor child.</hi> All Sonday night the Apprentices kept in a body in the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:113968:33"/> City, locked the City gates, but ſet no Guards upon them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you may ſee this buſineſſe proceeded meerly from the raſh and un-premeditated folly of Children, not from the advice of men: howſoever the Independent faction in the <hi>Houſe of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons</hi> have ſince aggravated it, to countenance their future cruelty and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines upon the City: Monday morning Sir <hi>Tho: Fairfax</hi> ſent a ſtrong party into the City, who fel upon this boyiſh rabble, routed and killed many, and ſhot poor Women great with child, ſitting in their ſtalls, one whereof the child lived two howers in her belly after her braines were ſhot out: a man likewiſe not knowing of their comming, as he was drinking milke at the corner of a ſtreet, was ſhot (as it were) in ſport: as they rid, they cried, <hi>Cuckolds keep your houſes,</hi> cutting and wounding all they met; <hi>Cromwell</hi> (who followed in the Reare ſafe enough, the Van having cleered the ſtreets before him) crying out to them <hi>to fire the City.</hi> Oh <hi>Oliver!</hi> what a barbarous <hi>John of Leyden</hi> art thou become? Oh <hi>London!</hi> how wretched a <hi>Munſter</hi> wilt thou become? at laſt they drove thoſe ſilly unarmed wretches into <hi>Leaden hall,</hi> and took many of them Priſoners, none of the Trained Bands nor Citizens appearing to help theſe poor Boyes, but leaving the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to get as bloudy and as boyiſh a Triumph over them, as they pleaſed, they are now impriſoned in <hi>Cromwell's</hi> ſhambles at <hi>White Hall.</hi> This is the truth of the buſineſſe, notwithſtanding the long-winded lying report made by Alderman <hi>Foukes,</hi> at the Commons Bar: a man that hath feathered his neſt well theſe miſerable times, and hath much publike money ſticking to his fingers; who when he gave in his Accompt before the generall Committee of Accounts, refuſed to give it in upon Oath (as other men did) alleaging <hi>Magna Charta, that no man was bound to accuſe himſelf:</hi> It ſhould ſeem he had ſomething in his Conſcience that would not endure the Teſt of an Oath: But he is one of the Godly, and therefore <hi>the good things of this world belong unto him.</hi> The Houſe of Commons (upon this occaſion) gave 1000l. to the Souldiers for this valorous exploit, and voted 1000. Foot, and 100. Horſe to be kept in the <hi>Tower.</hi> The Garriſons of <hi>White Hall</hi> and the <hi>Mewes</hi> to be ſtrengthned: three Barges capable of 50. Muſquetiers a piece to lie at <hi>White Hall</hi> for the Souldiers to convey them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to any landing place to diſperſe ſuch Water-men as ſhall
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:113968:34"/> aſſemble: The City Chaines to be taken away from their poſts, and a Commiſſion of Oyer and Terminer to Iſſue forth to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der more of theſe Children legally. The Major having kindled this fire in the City, ſtole out at a window diſgu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed, and hid his foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh head in the <hi>Tower.</hi> The Houſe of Commons (over-ruled by the <hi>Grandees</hi>) Voted a day of Thanks-giving for this Delivery. So bold are theſe Saints, as to mock Gods holy Name with impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous devotions to colour their deſignes.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="86" place="margin">86. The Lord <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiquin.</hi>
               </note>The Lord <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> preſident of <hi>Munſter,</hi> and Generall of the Army there, had a long time been heaved at by the <hi>Independent faction.</hi> The Lord <hi>Lyſle,</hi> (who gaped after his imployment) Sir <hi>John Temple, Cromwell,</hi> the Lord <hi>Broughill,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur,</hi> and Sir <hi>Adam Loftus,</hi> and others: who by obſtructing all ſupplies of Money, Ammunition, Victuall, Cloathes; laboured to mutiny and disband his Army, that they might ſend Schiſmaticks of their owne party to Lord it there, as they doe here, and keep <hi>Ireland</hi> as a Retreat for the Saints: for the better effecting whereof, they had ſent over many emiſſaries, whom they had commended to him, to be officers in his Army. When this would not doe, they printed Scandalous Articles againſt him, &amp; put infinite provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon him to incite him to doe that which they falſly accuſed him to have done already: But the many gallant ſervices he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed ſince the publiſhing thoſe Articles, gave them the lie, and confuted all their ſlanders; at laſt (under colour of ſending a ſupply of forces to him) they projected to ſurprize him, and bring him away priſoner: So that he hath ſuffered all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions that treacherous friends, and malicious enemies could put upon him. And lately (for the more cloſe conveiance of the deſigne) the Houſes ſent three Commiſſioners towards <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> to ſurvay his actions: but (as if it were purpoſely done) when the Commiſſioners came as far on their way as <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> about a dozen renegado Officers of his Army met the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners and turned them back againe. The ſaid Officers poſted up to the Parliament before the Commiſſioners, &amp; the 13. <hi>Aprill</hi> were called in to the Commons Barre, where they made a relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Houſe, to this purpoſe: That the Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made an expedition into the County of <hi>Kerry,</hi> upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, ſent for theſe Officers into his preſence Chamber, and told
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:113968:34"/> them, <hi>He intended to declare againſt the Army and Independent party in</hi> England, <hi>who kept the King and Parliament under a force: That he would ſtand for the liberty of the King and Parliament, and a free conference to ſettle Peace; and that he expected all his Officers ſhould joyne with him in ſo honourable an undertaking; but ſhould take an Oath of ſecreſie, before he diſcovered himſelfe farther to them.</hi> They anſwered, <hi>They could take no ſuch Oath before they knew whether they might with a ſafe Conſcience keep it:</hi> ſaying, <hi>they would be true to the Parliament.</hi> My Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> replied; <hi>So have I, and will be; delude me not with ambiguous words. Doe you mean this pretended Parliament?</hi> telling them farther, he had good, correſpondence with all the Presbyterians in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as well in the Parliament, as out of it; that he doubted not to goe through with his undertaking; and if the worſt hapned, to make good conditions for himſelf and his party. That he would make peace with the Lord <hi>Taffe,</hi> and that he knew the <hi>Independents</hi> in <hi>England</hi> were upon treaty with <hi>Owen, Roc, Oneal,</hi> who was a man of their humour, and loved to keep all in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion. They refuſing to joyne, he diſmiſſed them for <hi>England.</hi> The ſame day Letters from Captaine <hi>John Crowther,</hi> Vice-admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Seas from a Ship-board, were read in the Houſe, much to the ſame purpoſe, though not ſo large: wherein he ſaid, <hi>he had already blocked up all my Lord</hi> Inchiquines <hi>Havens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preſently <hi>Allen</hi> the <hi>Goldſmith</hi> moved,<note n="87" place="margin">87. <hi>Allen</hi> the Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith, moveth to put the Houſe to the touch, by ſome Covenant De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration.</note> That ſince the Lord <hi>Inchiquine</hi> had diſcovered that he had a correſpondency with the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in the Houſe, before they dealt with their Enemies without doores, they ſhould try who were their enemies within doors, by putting all men to ſome Covenant, Engagement, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, &amp;c. and Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſaid, That being to debate this buſineſſe to morrow, whoſoever with croſſe Arguments ſhall ſpin out the debate, and ſo retard our procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, (by my conſent) ſhall be noted with a black coale: to which was Anſwered, That this tended to take away freedome of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, which was the life of Parliaments and of all Councells: and was deſtructive to the very being of Parliaments. (It is not amiſſe to inſert here by way of digreſſion, what I formerly omitted) Sir <hi>Henry Mildmay</hi> long ſince moved, That 150. rich Guard-Coates of the Kings, might be ſold for 800.l. to finde fire and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:113968:35"/> candle for the Souldiers in <hi>White-Hall.</hi> The Queſtion put: The Speaker gave judgement, the <hi>Yeas,</hi> had it. Maſter <hi>Edw. Stephens</hi> declared the <hi>Noes,</hi> had it. They were unwilling to divide upon ſuch a Queſtion: But M. <hi>Stephens</hi> perſiſted; and <hi>Robert Reynolds</hi> ſaid aloud, <hi>notice ſhall be taken of him, for putting ſuch a diſhonour upon the Houſe.</hi> Upon the Diviſion, the <hi>Noes</hi> carried it by nine voices. Thereupon complaints was made againſt <hi>Reynolds,</hi> for attempting againſt the liberty of Voting, but no redreſſe. But to returne from my digreſſion. The next day 14 of <hi>Aprill,</hi> it was moved, that my Lord <hi>Inchiquins</hi> ſon, a child of 8 or 9 years old, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Schoole at <hi>Thiſtleworth,</hi> might be ſecured in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and kept for an Hoſtage. To which was Anſwered, That no man could give an Hoſtage. An Hoſtage muſt be given upon the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick faith, upon ſome ſtipulation, and muſt be ſo received, by mutuall agreement, you cannot puniſh the Child for the Fathers fault; yet he was Voted to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and ſent. My Lord <hi>Inchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quins</hi> Commiſſion as preſident of <hi>Munſter,</hi> and Generall of the Army, Voted voide, and no man to obey him, himſelfe Voted a Traytor: Yet no man examined upon Oath againſt him, nor any man ſent to take information of the buſineſſe into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and his profeſſed enemy the Lord <hi>Liſle</hi> is to goe Generall into <hi>Munſter</hi> in his roome; and the ſaid fugitive Officers all rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as if they had brought acceptable newes. This day <hi>Reynolds</hi> revived <hi>Allens</hi> motion for putting the Members to the Teſt, by ſome Covenant, Proteſtation, or Declaration ſubſcribed, That this is a free Parliament, and that they would live and die with this Parliament and Army: To which was Anſwered. 1. That by Ordinance of both Houſes, all men were enjoyned to take the Nationall Covenant. This Covenant is the true Touch-ſtone of the Parliament, and ſo agreed upon by the wiſdome of both Nations: Yet many ſit here who refuſe to obey this Ordinance: I know no reaſon therefore, why any man ſhould obey you in any other Ordinance of this nature: let us keep the old Covenant before we take any new. 2. It hath been moved in this Houſe, that the Oathes of Juſtices of the Peace and Sheriffes, might be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away: I hope you will not aboliſh legall Oathes, and impoſe illegall Oathes. This Houſe hath not ſo much Authority, as to adminiſter an Oath, much more to impoſe one: you muſt allow to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:113968:35"/> others that liberty of Conſcience which you demand for your ſelves. 3. Major <hi>Gray</hi> told you, my Lord <hi>Inchiquine</hi> ſaid he had correſpondency with all the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in the Houſe, who had made their peace with the King. But my Lord <hi>Inchiquine</hi> told him farther, the <hi>Independents</hi> were upon Treaty with <hi>Owen, Roc, Oneal,</hi> let them clear themſelves of that imputation firſt, before they give a purgation unto others, otherwiſe what you doe, will ſavour of force. 4. The true Touch-ſtone to try every mans inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity is, To examine, who have inriched themſelves by the cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the times and your ſervice: and who are impoveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. 5. This is a new device to Purge the Houſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Grandees</hi> of the Houſe have cantonized the Kingdome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween,<note n="88" place="margin">88. The Counties compelled to give thanks to the Houſes for their Votes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King.</note> them every man in his <hi>diviſion</hi> protecting the Country Committees, and receiving tribute from them in recompence of their protection; and <hi>Prideaux</hi> the Poſtmaſter being king of the <hi>Weſt Saxons,</hi> his Viceroy or Lord Deputy for the County of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet</hi> is that running Colonel <hi>John Pyne,</hi> who being often inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Sack, rules the Committee and County by inſpiration. <hi>Pyne</hi> and his Peers of the Committee, to pleaſe his Superiours, ſet on foot a draught of a <hi>Petition</hi> to be handed by the Country: <hi>Giving thanks to the Parliament for their</hi> 4 <hi>Votes againſt the King,</hi> and <hi>promiſed to live and die with the Parliament and Army,</hi> and <hi>deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the County might be freed from Malignants, Neuters, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates;</hi> which (in their interpretation) ſignifies <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> and <hi>moderate men,</hi> who will not daunce about the flame when the <hi>Independents</hi> make a bonfire of the Common-wealth. The Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne Diviſion of <hi>Somerſet-ſhire</hi> rejected the Petition: in the Weſterne Diviſion <hi>Pyne</hi> and his Committee ſending abroad their Sequeſtrators, with the Petition, (and threatning to take them for <hi>Malignants</hi> and <hi>ſequeſter them that refuſed</hi>) got many ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions; but the Subſcribers ſince better enformed of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and miſchief of thoſe Votes, retracted what they had done by a <hi>counter. Petition,</hi> wherein they declared that <hi>their Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the former Petition was contrary to their judgment and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and extorted by terror of Sequeſtrators, and threats of being ſequeſtred.</hi> This affront ſtung the Committee, and opened the eyes of the Country: as the like fooliſh attempt of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>H. Mildmay</hi> did the eyes of the County of <hi>Eſſex.</hi> Wherefore to find a playſter
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:113968:36"/> for this broken pate, Sergeant <hi>Wylde</hi> (he that hanged Capt. <hi>Burly</hi>) comming that Circuit, care was taken to have a ſelected Grand Jury of Schiſmaticks and Sequeſtrators blended together, who made a preſentment ſubſcribed by 19. of their hands, which Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant <hi>Wylde</hi> preſerved in his pocket; and upon Tueſday 18. <hi>April</hi> delivered with as much gravity as a ſet ſpeech and ſet ruffe could furniſh him withall in the Houſe of Commons, and was read and hearkened unto by the thriving godly, with as much attention, as pricking up of ears, and turning up of eyes could demonſtrate: the contents of this Preſentment were the ſame with the aforeſaid revoked Petition. Great care was taken to give thanks to the high Sheriffe and Grand Jury, who had ſo freely delivered the ſenſe of that well-affected County: and as much care taken to improve this Talent and put it to intereſt throughout the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Colonel <hi>Purefoy</hi> is now at this worke in <hi>Warwick-ſhire.</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Haſterig</hi> about <hi>Newcaſtle:</hi> others in other places. Pitifull Crutches to ſupport a crippled reputation, which now halts and begs for relief worſe then their owne maymed Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers do, and with as bad ſucceſſe; they have juggled themſelves out of credit, and would fain juggle themſelves in again. Behold the wiſdome of our <hi>Grandees,</hi> wiſe, religious, new-modelled Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who have brought themſelves and the whole Kingdome into theſe deplorable, contemptible ſtraights; take notice of your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative</hi> you that are <hi>Repreſented,</hi> call them to a <hi>ſeaſonable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count:</hi> But whither doth my zeale carry me? I ſhall anon ſtumble upon a new-fangled Treaſon to be declared againſt me.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="89" place="margin">89. Mens tongues tied up by an Ordinance.</note>Friday, 21. <hi>April,</hi> an Ordinance was preſented to the Houſe, intituled, <hi>For ſuppreſſing all Tumults and Inſurrections,</hi> (the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Safety at <hi>Darby houſe</hi> had before an ample power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon them for that purpoſe; but <hi>guilty conſciences</hi> though they be <hi>ſafe,</hi> are never <hi>ſecure;</hi> like <hi>Cain,</hi> they think that every man will ſlay them) it was paſſed after ſome amendments to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>That any three Committee men ſhall have power to Impriſon and Sequeſter all ſuch as ſhall actually adhere to any that ſhall raiſe, or endeavour to raiſe Tumults and Inſurrections, or ſhall ſpeak or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh any thing reproachfull to the Parliament, or their proceedings:</hi> Behold here an exciſe (amounting to the value of all you have) ſet upon every light word: A man made an offender for a <hi>word</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:113968:36"/> to the <hi>utter ruine</hi> of him and his poſterity, under colour of <hi>defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Lawes, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Properties,</hi> you are <hi>cheated of them all,</hi> and <hi>reduced</hi> to meer and abſolute <hi>ſlavery</hi> and <hi>beggery:</hi> you are not maſters of your own carkaſſes, yet your mouths are buttoned up, you muſt not be allowed that ſilly comfort of venting your griefs by way of complaint: what Tyrant was ever ſo barbarous, ſo indiſcreet as to do the like? It was moved that Offendors of this kind might be bound to the good Behaviour, and the offence proved openly at the Aſſizes or Seſſions, before ſo deſtructive a puniſhment be inflicted. There are three principles in law, of which the Laws are very tender, and will not ſuffer them to be touched but upon great offences, cleer proofs, and exact forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities obſerved; <hi>life, liberty,</hi> and <hi>eſtate,</hi> by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of Right,</hi> and many other Statutes; theſe principles are ſo ſacred, that nothing but the Law can meddle with them, <hi>Nemo impriſonetur aut diſſeiſietur niſi per legale judicium parium ſuorum,</hi> you have made the people ſhed their money and bloud abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, pretending <hi>defence of Religion, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> let them now at laſt (being a time of peace) enjoy what they have ſo dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paid for; and delay them not with a pretended neceſſity of your owne making, you now make all that is, or can be neer and deer to them lyable to the paſſions of three Committee men to judge and execute according to their diſcretion without Law, or ſo much as a formality thereof: And yet both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have often heretofore offered to aboliſh thoſe Committees as men whoſe wickedneſſe and folly they and the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome were aſhamed of: The <hi>Grandees</hi> of the Parliament and Army when the Houſes are called and full, have reſolved to draw their Forces nearer about the Towne, and by that terrour to try the temper of the Houſes; ſuch Members as will not comply with them, they will with freſh Charges purge out of the Houſes, and publiſh baſe and infamous ſcandalls againſt them, to which if they ſubmit with ſilence, they betray their reputations for ever; and ſpare the credits of their jugling enemies. If they make any defence for their honours by way of apology, they ſhall be brought within the compaſſe of this devouring, enſlaving Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, <hi>as men that reproach the Parliament and their proceedings.</hi> Thus the ſame whip ſhall hang over the ſhoulders of the <hi>Preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:113968:37"/> party</hi> (who wil not agree to <hi>King-depoſing, Anarchy,</hi> &amp; <hi>Schiſm</hi>) as it did formerly over the <hi>Kings party.</hi> And the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> ſhall be ſqueezed into the <hi>Independents</hi> coffers, as formerly the <hi>King's party</hi> were, ſo long as they had any thing to loſe; for the whole earth is little enough for theſe Saints, who are never ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with money and bloud, although they never looke towards Heaven but through the ſpectacles of this world. The old <hi>elogium</hi> and character of the Engliſh Nation was, that they were, <hi>Hilaris gens, cui libera mens, &amp; libera lingua.</hi> But now (Country-men) your <hi>tongues</hi> are in the <hi>ſtocks,</hi> your <hi>bodies</hi> in every <hi>gaole,</hi> your <hi>ſouls</hi> in the <hi>darke,</hi> and <hi>eſtates</hi> in the <hi>mercy</hi> of thoſe that have <hi>no mercy,</hi> and at the <hi>diſcretion</hi> of thoſe that have no <hi>diſcretion:</hi> Farewell <hi>Engliſh Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="conclusions">
               <head>
                  <note n="90" place="margin">90. Generall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions.</note>Out of theſe Premiſes I ſhall draw theſe Concluſions following:</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <note n="1" place="margin">1. The Grandees have ſubverted the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdome, and why.</note>1. THe <hi>engaged Party</hi> have laid the <hi>Axe</hi> to the very <hi>root</hi> of <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Parliaments:</hi> they have caſt all the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and ſecrets of Government, both by Kings and Parliaments, before the vulgar; like pearle before ſwine: and have taught both the Souldiery and people to looke ſo far into them, as to ravell back all Governments, to the firſt principles of nature: he that ſhakes fundamentalls, means to take down the fabrick. Nor have they been carefull to ſave the materialls for poſterity. What theſe negative Statiſts will ſet up in the room of theſe ruined buildings doth not appeare; only I will ſay, <hi>they have made the people there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſo cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us and ſo arrogant, that they wil never find humility enough to ſubmit to a Civill rule;</hi> their ayme therefore from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was to rule them <hi>by the power of the Sword,</hi> a military Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracie or Olgarchy, as now they do. Amongſt the aincient Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, <hi>Tentare Arcana Imperii,</hi> to profane the myſteries of State was Treaſon; becauſe there can be no forme of Government without its proper myſteries: which are no longer myſteries then while they are concealed. Ignorance, and admiration ariſing from Ignorance, are the parents of civil devotion and obedience, though not of Theologicall.<note n="2" place="margin">2. They have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the Church.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor have theſe <hi>Grandees</hi> and their party in the Synode, dealt more kindly with the Church then with the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:113968:37"/> whoſe reverend Myſteries; their Pulpits and holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments; and all the functions of the Miniſtery are by their conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence prophaned by the clouted ſhooe; the baſeſt and loweſt of the people making themſelves Prieſts: and with a blind diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red zeal Preaching ſuch Doctrine as their private Spirits (ſpirits of illuſion) dictate to them: But let them know, that their burning zeal without knowledge, is like hell-fire without light. Yet the greateſt wonder of all is,<note place="margin">The Sacrament of the Lords Supper diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, and why?</note> That they ſuffer the Lords Supper (that Sacrament of Corroboration) to be ſo much neglected in almoſt all the Churches in the Kingdome. Is it becauſe men uſually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they receive our Saviour, (that bleſſed gueſt) ſweep the houſe cleane, caſting out of their hearts, (thoſe living Temples of the holy Ghoſt) <hi>Pride, Ambition, Covetouſneſſe, Envy, Hatred, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> and all other unclean Spirits, to make fit roome to entertaine <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that prince of peace: whereby the people having their mindes prepared for <hi>Peace, Charity, and Reconciliation;</hi> may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily ſpoile the trade of our <hi>Grandees,</hi> who can no longer maintaine their uſurped dominion over them, then they can keep them diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united with quarrels and feudes; and uphold thoſe Badges of factions, and tearmes of diſtinction and ſeparation: <hi>Cavaleers, Round-heades, Malignants, Well-affected, Presbyterians and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendents?</hi> or is it becauſe they fear, if the Church were ſetled in peace &amp; unity, it would be a means to unite the Common-wealth, as a quiet cheerfull minde often cureth a diſtempered body? I will not take upon me to judge another mans ſervant; but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuſpect this is done out of deſigne, not out of peeviſhneſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That theſe <hi>Grandees</hi> governe by power,<note n="3" place="margin">3. The Grandees rule by the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytrary power of the Sword, not by the Lawes.</note> not by lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and the the Lawes of the Land, (which was my laſt aſſertion) appears by</p>
               <p n="1">1. The many Garriſons they keep up, and numerous Army they keep in pay to over-power the whole Kingdome, more then at firſt the Parliament Voted.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Their compelling the Parliament to put the whole Militia of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Jreland,</hi> by Land &amp; Sea, into the power of Sir <hi>Tho: Fairfax</hi> and their party.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nor do they think the Laws of the Land extenſive enough for their purpoſes; therefore they piece them out with Arbitrary Ordinances, Impeachments before the Lords, and Marſhall Law, which is now grown to that height, that the Councell of War, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and judge Advocate of the Army doe uſually ſend forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:113968:38"/> to ſtay ſuites, and releaſe judgements at Law, or elſe to attend the Councell of Warre, whereſoever they ſit, to ſhew cauſe to the contrary: And when Lieut. Colonell <hi>Lylborne</hi> was ordered to be brought to the Kings Bench-Barre, upon his <hi>habeas Corpus,</hi> Eaſter Terme, 1648. <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſent word to the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the <hi>Tower</hi> not to bring him, and <hi>Cromwell</hi> was obeyed, not the Judges. Thus the Laws of the Land are daily baffled, that men may be accuſtomed to Arbitrary Government, and thoſe actions which no Law of the Land calls a crime, may be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Treaſon when our <hi>Grandees</hi> pleaſe to have it ſo.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Their <hi>allowing Mony to ſome Committees</hi> to <hi>reward Informers, Spies,</hi> &amp; <hi>Intelligencers</hi> to <hi>betray even their neareſt friends</hi> &amp; <hi>relations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Their holding <hi>Honeſt, Generous,</hi> and <hi>Grave</hi> men in ſuſpicion, and making the Houſes of Parliament and Army ſnares to them, expelling them with falſe and extrajudiciall Accuſations.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Their owning diſhoneſt, baſe minded men, that have cheated the State, as inſtruments fit to be confided in, and aſſociate with them in time of danger.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Their impoveriſhing the people with confuſed Taxes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Trade, and obſtructing of the mint, and thereby breaking their ſpirits.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Their changing and dividing the Militia of <hi>London</hi> purpoſely to weaken it.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Their not reſtoring to the Countries their Militia, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting them to defend their owne houſes as formerly.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Their nouriſhing factions in the Common-wealth, Schiſmes in the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ch.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Expelling learned Divines to let in ignorant men. All theſe are Tyrannicall policies grounded upon the old principle; That a Tyrant ſhould deprive His Subjects of all things that may nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh courage, ſtrength, knowledge, mutuall confidence and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity amongſt them; which Maxime the beſt Politicians ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines the whole Syſteme or method of Tyrannicall Government.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note n="4" place="margin">4. The Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents divide the Taxes, Spo les, &amp; Preferments of the Land be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.</note>4. As this encroaching faction have uſurped all the Military and Civill power of both Kingdomes; ſo they have Monopolized all the great Offices, Rich imployments, and Treaſure of the Land; They are cleerly the predominant party in all money Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees; They give daily to one another for pretended Services, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ars, and looſſes, great ſummes of money: many of their lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſſes
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:113968:38"/> I have already ſet down, They gave lately to Colonel <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> Governour of the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> for his Table 20l. a week, 1000l. in money, and 500l. a year land; to Major Gen. <hi>Skippon</hi> 1000l. <hi>per annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> land of Inheritance; to Col. <hi>Mitton</hi> 5000l. mony. All the cheating, covetous, ambitious perſons of the land, are uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together under the name and title of <hi>The Godly, the Saints,</hi> &amp;c. and ſhare the fat of the land between them, few of them pay any Taxes, but all the Land paies Tribute to them. It is thought this Faction, their under-Agents and Factors have coſt this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth above 20 millions never laid forth in any publike ſervice. Nay, the Treaſurers and Publicans of this Faction have clipped and waſhed moſt of the mony that comes into their fingers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they pay it forth, knowing that any mony that comes out of their fingers will be accepted; two Gold-ſmiths are thought to be dealers this way, yet they lay the blame on the Scottiſh Army, as the Cuckow laies her brood in other neſts.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Having thus imped their wings for flight,<note n="5" place="margin">5. The Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents provided of Places of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat to flie to.</note> they have provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded themſelves of places of retreat in caſe they cannot make good their ſtanding in <hi>England; Ireland</hi> is kept unprovided for, that they may find roome in it when neceſſity drives them thither. If their hopes faile in Ireland, they have <hi>New-England, Bermudas, Barbadas,</hi> the <hi>Carybi</hi> Iſles, the Iſle of <hi>Providence, Eleutheria, Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonia,</hi> and other places to retreat to, and lay up the ſpoiles of <hi>England</hi> in: nay, they uſually ſend cheſts and veſſels with mony, plate, and goods beyond Sea, with Paſſes from the two Speakers, <hi>To let them paſſe without ſearching:</hi> the Navy is in their power to accommodate their flight, and by their Inſtruments called <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> they have taken up many Children and ſent them before to be Slaves and drudges to the Godly in their ſchiſmaticall Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: as the Turke takes up Tribute-children from the Chriſtians to furniſh his nurſery of Janiſaries: and ſo they have their Agents that buy up all the Gold they can get: <hi>Cromwell</hi> not long ſince offered 11000l. in ſilver for 10000l. in gold; beſides, he is well furniſhed with the Kings Jewels taken in his Cabinet at <hi>Nazeby,</hi> many of them known jewels, as the <hi>Harry,</hi> and the <hi>Eliſabeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Nor ſhall the vulgar ſort of <hi>Independents</hi> either in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Army,</hi> or <hi>City,</hi> fare better then the reſt of the <hi>Kingdome.</hi>
                  <note n="6" place="margin">6. The vulgar In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents but props and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties to the Grandees.</note> The <hi>Grandees</hi> both of <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Army</hi> endevouring to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and draw all the power of both Houſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:113968:39"/> the Committee of <hi>Derby-houſe,</hi> conſiſting but of 20. or 30. the reſt of the Independent Members will find their power diſſolved in the adjournment, and ſwallowed up by that Committee, and rheir ſervices forgotten: nor ſhal they have any power in the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi> which is the only quarrell between them and the King: the <hi>Grandees</hi> diſdaining to have ſo many Partners in that which they have got by their own wits; for know that the <hi>Grandees</hi> have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies been winnowing the Parliament. Firſt, they winnowed out the <hi>moderate men</hi> under the notion of the <hi>Kings party;</hi> then the <hi>Preſbyterians;</hi> and now they will winnow forth the <hi>lighter</hi> and more <hi>chaffy ſort</hi> of <hi>Independents,</hi> who ſtand for the <hi>Liberty of the people;</hi> a thing which <hi>Cromwell</hi> now calleth, <hi>a fancy not to be enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for;</hi> and ſo they will bring all power into their own hands. Thus having contracted the <hi>Parliament</hi> into a <hi>Committee of Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> they will adjourne themſelves (though the Parliament cannot) to <hi>Oxford,</hi> or ſome other place which they more confide in then <hi>London:</hi> and this is <hi>the ſetling the Kingdom without the King,</hi> they ſo much ayme at: and which they had rather the people ſhould be brought to practically and by inſenſible degrees, then by Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions held forth to them before hand, or by politick Lectures in the Pulpit. Thus is it decreed that this Caball of Godly men at <hi>Derby-houſe</hi> ſhall with a Military Ariſtocracy or rather Oligar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, rule this Nation with a rod of Iron, and break them in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces like a Potters veſſell.</p>
               <p>Obſerve that the Ordinance by which the Committee of <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by-houſe</hi> is revived, and the <hi>additions</hi> of power to it, are purpoſely penned in ſuch ambiguous tearms, that <hi>he that hath the Sword in his hand, may make what conſtruction of them he pleaſeth:</hi> neither were they clearly penned, is it in the power of the Houſes (being but the Truſtees of the people) to transfer or delegate their truſt to a leſſer number of men: a truſt not being transferable by law, and the people having choſen a Parliament, not a Committee to look to their ſafety and peace.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <note n="7" place="margin">7. The Army hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Peace and Setlement.</note>7. The <hi>Grandees</hi> of the Parliament and Army have brought the Kingdome to ſo miſerable a condition, that they have left no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in <hi>England</hi> able to ſettle peace: the King is a cloſe Priſoner to the Army, therefore all he ſhall doe will be clearly void in law by reaſon of <hi>Dures:</hi> The Parliament is in Wardſhip to them, who keep armed Guards upon them, Garriſons round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:113968:39"/> them, and by illegall Accuſations, Blancke Impeachments, threatning Remonſtrances, and Declarations, &amp;c. fright away many Members and compell the reſt to Vote and un-Vote what they pleaſe, whereby all the Parliament doth is void and null in Law <hi>ab initio,</hi> it being no free Parliament but a Sub-committee to the Army, and living as the Aegyptians did under vaſſalage to their own <hi>Mamaluchi</hi> or Mercenaries: The people therefore muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve either to have <hi>no Army,</hi> or <hi>no Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. They have put out the eyes of the Kingdome,<note n="8" place="margin">8. The two Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</note> the two Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and have brought the whole Land to make ſport before them, knowing that <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> as well as <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> are enemies to their barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, irrationall, and Ruſſian way of Government.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Many honeſt men took part with this Parliament,<note n="9" place="margin">9. Many honeſt men ſeduced by faire pretences, took part with them; never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to leave their firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave King, and Kingdome.</note> ſeduced by thoſe fair pretences of <hi>defending Religion, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> which they firſt held forth to the people; and being unwilling to have a <hi>Parliament conquered</hi> by <hi>the Sword,</hi> not thinking it poſſible that a <hi>prevailing Faction</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould ſo far prevaricate as to <hi>conſpire to enſlave King, Parliament, and Kingdome, to ſubvert the Laws, Liberties and fundamentall Government of the Land,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which <hi>they and their Poſterity were, and were likely to be ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily governed, and betray Religion unto Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, and ſhare the ſpoiles of the Common-wealth between them, and think of enriching themſelves with them in foraine lands;</hi> yet many at the beginning much diſliked that <hi>Religion</hi> ſhould be uſed as an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient</hi> to the carrying on of a <hi>Civill War,</hi> and that <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> ſhould have ſo great a ſtroak in managing the buſineſſe: yet were pacified with this conſideration, that we muſt refuſe no helps in our defence: if a man be aſſaulted by Thieves on the high way, he will not refuſe to joyne with Schiſmaticks or Turks in a common defence; the ſame authority that then countenanced thoſe Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks (it was hoped) would be able to diſcountenance them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain when the work was done. But the <hi>Grandees</hi> of the Houſes (having other deſignes) had ſo often purged the Houſes, that they left few honeſt moderate men in them to oppoſe their projects, ſtill bringing in Schiſmaticks and men of their owne intereſts, by enforced &amp; undue Elections, into their rooms; and ſo by inſenſible degrees, new modelled the Houſe ſutable to their owne corrupt deſires, and new modelled this Army accordingly: ſo that the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:113968:40"/> people (who had no intention to be intruſted ſo far) were ſtep by ſtep ſo far engaged before they were aware, that they could not draw their feet back, and do now find (to their grief) that the Bit is in their mouths, the ſaddle faſt girt on their galled backs, and theſe Rank riders mounted; who will ſpur them (not only out of their Eſtates, Lawes, and Liberties) but into Hell with renewed Treaſons, new Oaths, Covenants and Engagements, if they take not the more heed, and be not the more reſolute: they have chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their old honeſt principles, and their old friends, who bore the firſt brunt of the buſineſſe; and have taken new principles and friends in their roome, ſutable to their preſent deſperate deſignes, and now (that they have ſqueezed what they can out of the Kings party) they think of ſequeſtring their old friends, becauſe they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to their old principles.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <note n="10" place="margin">10. Who are the King's bittereſt enemies.</note>10. Amongſt thoſe that are moſt bitter againſt the King, his own Servants (eſpecially the <hi>Judaſſes</hi> of the Committee of the Revenue that carry his purſe, and have fingered more of his mony and goods then they can or dare give an account for) are the greateſt Zealots, thoſe that take upon them imployments about his Revenue, and ſhare what allowances to themſelves they pleaſe for their pains; thoſe that buy in for trifles old ſleeping penſions, that have not been payed nor allowed this thirty years, and pay themſelves all arrears: thoſe that rent parcells of the Kings Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, for the eighth or tenth part of the worth, as <hi>Cor: Holland,</hi> who renteth for 200l. <hi>per annum,</hi> as much of his Eſtate as is worth 1600l. or 1800l. <hi>per annum:</hi> Thus you ſee the Lion (Lord of the forreſt) growing ſick and weak, become a prey, and is goared by the Oxe, bitten by the Dog, yea and kicked by the Aſſe; Look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this preſident you Kings and Princes, and call to mind exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of old, that of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> &amp; others, <hi>leſt by exalting your ſelves too high, you provoke God to cast you too low.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="epilogue">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</note>
                  <hi>I Am not Ignorant that there is a naturall purging, a naturall phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomy, belonging to politicke, as well as to naturall bodies: and that ſome good humours are alwaies evacuated with the bad, yet I cannot but deplore what I have obſerved, That the honeſteſt and juſteſt men of both ſides (ſuch as, if they have done evill, did it becauſe they thought it good; ſuch as were carried aſide with ſpecious pretences, and many of them ſeduced by pulpit-Devils who transformed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:113968:40"/> into Angels of light) have alwaies fared worſe then other men, as if this difference between the King &amp; Parliament were but a</hi> ſyncre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmus <hi>or illuſion againſt honeſt men: nay, I do farther fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee that in the period and cloſing up of this Tragedy, they will fare worſt of all, becauſe they have not taken a liberty to enrich themſelves with pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick spoyles, and fat themſelves by eating out the bowels of their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but are grown lean and poor by their integrity; whereby being diſabled to buy friendſhip in the daies of trouble, they will be put upon it, to pay other mens reckonings: When</hi> Verres <hi>was Praetor of</hi> Sicily <hi>he had with wonderful corruptions pillaged that Province; and at the ſame time the Praetor of</hi> Sardinia <hi>being ſentenced for depeculating and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing that Province,</hi> Timarchides, Verres <hi>correſpondent at</hi> Rome, <hi>writ a very anxious Letter to him, giving him warning of it: But</hi> Verres <hi>in a jolly humour anſwered him,</hi> that the Praetor of <hi>Sardinia</hi> was a foole, and had extorted no more from the Sardinians then would ſerve his own turn; but himſelf had gathered up ſuch rich Booties amongſt the Sicilians, that the very overplus thereof would dazle the eyes of the Senate, and blind them ſo that they ſhould not ſee his faults: <hi>ſuch (I foreſee) will be the lot of the more juſt and modeſt men, who ſhall be guilty becauſe they were fools; as the other ſort ſhall be innocent becauſe they were knaves: whatſoever befalls (you cleer and innoxious ſouls) be not aſhamed, be not afraid of your integrity: if this Kingdom be a fit habitation for honeſt men, God wil provide you a habitation here; if it be not capable of honesty, God will take you away from the evills to come, and poure out all the vials of his wrath upon this totally and univerſally corrupted Nation, this incurable people;</hi> Qui nec vitia ſua nec eorum remedia ferre poteſt: <hi>for my own part, (if I am not ſuch already) I hope God will make me ſuch a man,</hi> Quem neque pauperies, neque mors, neque vincula terrent; <hi>and if</hi> Moſes <hi>in a heroick zeal, to draw a remiſſion of the peoples ſin from God, deſired to be blotted out of his booke, (the book of life) and S.</hi> Paul <hi>to be</hi> Anathema <hi>for his brethren, why ſhould not I (with relation to my ſelf, &amp; ſubmiſſion to Chriſt) ſay,</hi> oportet unum mori pro populo, <hi>it is fit one man die for the people, and devote my ſelf to death for my Country, as the Family of the</hi> Decii <hi>in ancient</hi> Rome <hi>were wont to do? I have read and admired their examples, why not imitate them? is it becauſe (as</hi> Machiavell <hi>ſaith) the Chriſtian Religion doth too much breake, enfeeble, and cowardize the ſpirit of man, by perſecuting
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:113968:41"/> &amp; ſubduing nature by denying her due Liberty, &amp; tying her to be more paſſive then active:</hi> At facere &amp; pati fortia Romanum, imo Chriſtianum eſt: <hi>or is it becauſe in this generall deluge of ſin and corruption, all publick ſpirit, and all excellency in virtue is accounted a degree of madneſſe? or is it becauſe of the corrupt Judgement of theſe times, which makes a man more infamous for his puniſhment, then for his ſin? and therefore Heroick acts are out of faſhion; the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and Ceremonies of death, are more taken notice of then Death it ſelf: theſe follies weigh not with me.</hi> Sublimis an humi putreſcam, parvi refert. <hi>The theif upon the Croſſe found a ready way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: how much more an honeſt man? many a man out of priſon ſteps into Heaven, no man out of Paradiſe ever found the way thither:</hi> Sale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſa ſit via, modo certa, modo expedita; alte ſuccinctus ad iter me accingo.</p>
               <p>THe premiſes conſidered, I do here in the name &amp; behalf of all the free Commons of <hi>England,</hi> declare and proteſt that there is no free nor legall <hi>Parliament</hi> ſitting in <hi>England;</hi> but that the two Houſes ſit under a viſible, actuall, and a horrid force of a muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous <hi>Army,</hi> and of a ſmall party of both Houſes conſpiring and engaged with the ſaid <hi>Army,</hi> to deſtroy, expell and murder, with falſe Accuſations, and blank and illegall Impeachments and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, the reſt of their fellow Members, who ſate in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> doing their duty, when the two Speakers with a ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Members ſecretly fled away to the <hi>Army,</hi> and ſate in Councell with them, contriving how to enſlave <hi>King, Parliament, City,</hi> and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and how to raiſe Taxes at their pleaſure, which they ſhare amongſt themſelves and their party, under the name and title of the Godly, the Saints: And afterwards they brought the <hi>Army</hi> up to <hi>London,</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>City</hi> in hoſtile manner; A deſigne far exceeding the Plot of <hi>Jermine, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, &amp;c.</hi> to bring up the <hi>Northerne Army to London to over-awe the Parliament:</hi> I doe farther proteſt, that the two Houſes have ſate under the ſaid force, ever ſince the 6. of <hi>Aug.</hi> laſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all they have done, and all they ſhall doe, in the condition they now ſit in, is <hi>void</hi> and <hi>nul</hi> in Law, <hi>ab initio,</hi> by their owne doctrine and judgement included in their Ordinance of the 20. of <hi>Aug.</hi> laſt; whereby they <hi>nul</hi> and <hi>void, ab initio,</hi> all Votes, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, &amp;c. paſſed from the 26. <hi>July</hi> 1647. to the 6. <hi>Aug.</hi> following.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
